//(frail AND (frail OR phenotype OR index)) AND "chronic kidney disease" AND causes
//(frail[All Fields] AND (frail[All Fields] OR ("phenotype"[MeSH Terms] OR "phenotype"[All Fields]) OR ("abstracting and indexing as topic"[MeSH Terms] OR ("abstracting"[All Fields] AND "indexing"[All Fields] AND "topic"[All Fields]) OR "abstracting and indexing as topic"[All Fields] OR "index"[All Fields]))) AND "chronic kidney disease"[All Fields] AND ("etiology"[Subheading] OR "etiology"[All Fields] OR "causes"[All Fields] OR "causality"[MeSH Terms] OR "causality"[All Fields])
//
1. Int Urol Nephrol. 2018 Aug;50(8):1505-1510. doi: 10.1007/s11255-018-1900-3. Epub 
2018 Jun 4.

Kidney function and cognitive decline in frail elderly: two faces of the same
coin?

Coppolino G(1), Bolignano D(2), Gareri P(3), Ruberto C(3), Andreucci M(4),
Ruotolo G(5), Rocca M(3), Castagna A(3).

Author information: 
(1)Nephrology and Dialysis Unit, "Pugliese-Ciaccio" General Hospital, Via Michele
Torcia, 4, 88100, Catanzaro, Italy. gcoppolino@hotmail.it.
(2)Institute of Clinical Physiology, CNR - Italian National Council of Research, 
Reggio Calabria, Italy.
(3)Center for Cognitive Disorders and Dementia, Azienda Sanitaria Provinciale di 
Catanzaro, Catanzaro, Italy.
(4)Renal Unit, Department of Health Sciences, "Magna Graecia" University,
Catanzaro, Italy.
(5)Geriatric Unit, "Pugliese-Ciaccio" General Hospital, Catanzaro, Italy.

BACKGROUND AND AIMS: Cognitive and renal impairment are pervasive among elderly
frails, a high-risk, geriatric sub-population with peculiar clinical
characteristics. In a series of frail individuals with non-advanced chronic
kidney disease (CKD), we aimed at assessing the entity of functional, general
health and cognitive impairment and the possible relationship between these types
of dysfunction and the severity of renal impairment.
METHODS: 2229 geriatric subjects were screened for frailty and CKD. Severity of
CKD was assessed by eGFR (CKD-EPI formula). Frailty was established by the Fried 
Index. Functional, general health and cognitive status were assessed by validated
score measures.
RESULTS: Final analysis included 271 frail CKD subjects (162 women, 109 men).
Mean eGFR was 64.25 ± 25.04 mL/min/1.73 m2. Prevalence of mild-to-moderate CKD
(stage 3-4) was 44%. Twenty-six percent of patients had severe cognitive
impairment, while mild and moderate impairment was found in 7 and 67% of
individuals, respectively. All subjects had poor functional and general health
status. Cognitive capacities significantly decreased across CKD stages (p for
trend < 0.0001). In fully adjusted multivariate analyses, cognitive status
remained an independent predictor of eGFR (β = 0.465; p < 0.0001).
CONCLUSIONS: Mild-to-moderate CKD is highly pervasive among frail elderly
individuals and the severity of renal dysfunction is independently correlated
with that of cognitive impairment. Future studies are advocated to clarify
whether the combination of kidney and mental dysfunction may portend a higher
risk of worsen outcomes in this high-risk population.

DOI: 10.1007/s11255-018-1900-3 
PMID: 29868939  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


2. Diabetologia. 2018 Jul;61(7):1503-1516. doi: 10.1007/s00125-018-4547-9. Epub 2018
Feb 7.

Diabetes in the older patient: heterogeneity requires individualisation of
therapeutic strategies.

Schernthaner G(1), Schernthaner-Reiter MH(2).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Medicine 1, Rudolfstiftung Hospital, Juchgasse 25, 1030, Vienna,
Austria. guntram.schernthaner@meduniwien.ac.at.
(2)Clinical Division of Endocrinology and Metabolism, Department of Internal
Medicine III, Medical University of Vienna, Währinger Gürtel, 18-20 1090, Vienna,
Austria. marie.schernthaner-reiter@meduniwien.ac.at.

Owing to the worldwide increase in life expectancy, the high incidence of
diabetes in older individuals and the improved survival of people with diabetes, 
about one-third of all individuals with diabetes are now older than 65 years.
Evidence is accumulating that type 2 diabetes is associated with cognitive
impairment, dementia and frailty. Older people with diabetes have significantly
more comorbidities, such as myocardial infarction, stroke, peripheral arterial
disease and renal impairment, compared with those without diabetes. However, as a
consequence of the increased use of multifactorial risk factor intervention, a
considerable number of older individuals can now survive for many years without
any vascular complications. Given the heterogeneity of older individuals with
type 2 diabetes, an individualised approach is warranted, which must take into
account the health status, presence or absence of complications, and life
expectancy. In doing so, undertreatment of otherwise healthy older individuals
and overtreatment of those who are frail may be avoided. Specifically,
overtreatment of hyperglycaemia in older patients is potentially harmful; in
particular, insulin and sulfonylureas should be avoided or, if necessary, used
with caution. Instead, glucose-dependent drugs that do not induce hypoglycaemia
are preferable since older patients with diabetes and impaired kidney function
are especially vulnerable to this adverse event.

DOI: 10.1007/s00125-018-4547-9 
PMID: 29417185  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


3. Vascular. 2018 Aug;26(4):425-431. doi: 10.1177/1708538118756690. Epub 2018 Feb 5.

Peripheral artery disease is associated with frailty in chronic hemodialysis
patients.

Okuyama M(1), Takeuchi H(2)(3), Uchida HA(4), Kakio Y(2), Okuyama Y(2),
Umebayashi R(2), Wada K(5), Sugiyama H(6), Sugimoto K(7), Rakugi H(7), Kasahara
S(1), Wada J(2).

Author information: 
(1)1 Department of Cardiovascular Surgery, Okayama University Hospital, Okayama, 
Japan.
(2)2 Department of Nephrology, Rheumatology, Endocrinology and Metabolism,
Okayama University Graduate School of Medicine, Dentistry and Pharmaceutical
Sciences, Okayama, Japan.
(3)3 Department of Internal Medicine, Innoshima General Hospital, Hiroshima,
Japan.
(4)4 Department of Chronic Kidney Disease and Cardiovascular Disease, Okayama
University Graduate School of Medicine, Dentistry and Pharmaceutical Sciences,
Okayama, Japan.
(5)5 Division of Nephrology and Dialysis, Department of Internal Medicine, Nippon
Kokan Fukuyama Hospital, Hiroshima, Japan.
(6)6 Department of Human Resource Development of Dialysis Therapy for Kidney
Disease, Okayama University Graduate School of Medicine, Dentistry and
Pharmaceutical Sciences, Okayama, Japan.
(7)7 Department of Geriatric and General Medicine, Osaka University Graduate
School of Medicine, Osaka, Japan.

Objectives The clinical condition of frailty is a common problem in the elderly
population. However, the relationship between peripheral artery disease and
frailty in hemodialysis patients remains unknown. The aim of this study was to
identify the relationships between peripheral artery disease and frailty in
Japanese chronic hemodialysis patients. Methods A total of 362 chronic
hemodialysis patients who regularly visited six institutions were enrolled. To
evaluate frailty, the modified Fried's frailty phenotype adjusted for Japanese
were used. Peripheral artery disease was defined as ankle-brachial index <0.9.
Results Of 362 patients, 62 patients (17.1%) were categorized as peripheral
artery disease group and 300 patients (82.9%) as Non-peripheral artery disease
group. The prevalence of frailty in the peripheral artery disease group was
significantly higher than in the Non-peripheral artery disease group (34% vs.
18%, P = 0.0103). Non-shunt side grip strength was significantly stronger in the 
Non-peripheral artery disease group (23.6 kg vs. 17.0 kg, P < 0.0001). Thigh
circumferences were also significantly larger in the Non-peripheral artery
disease group (41.7 cm vs. 39.7 cm, P = 0.0054). A multivariate logistic
regression analysis demonstrated that the factors independently associated with
peripheral artery disease were as follows: frailty (odds ratio = 2.06, 95%
confidence interval 1.09-3.89) and myocardial infarction (odds ratio = 3.74, 95% 
confidence interval 2.05-6.83). Conclusions It is concluded that peripheral
artery disease is closely associated with frailty in hemodialysis patients.

DOI: 10.1177/1708538118756690 
PMID: 29402196  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


4. Acta Diabetol. 2018 Apr;55(4):323-330. doi: 10.1007/s00592-017-1094-7. Epub 2018 
Jan 11.

Levels of serum uric acid at admission for hypoglycaemia predict 1-year
mortality.

Bonaventura A(1), Gallo F(2), Carbone F(3), Liberale L(3)(4), Maggi D(2), Sacchi 
G(5), Dallegri F(3)(6), Montecucco F(3)(6)(7), Cordera R(2).

Author information: 
(1)First Clinic of Internal Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, University
of Genoa, 6 Viale Benedetto XV, 16132, Genoa, Italy. aldobon85@gmail.com.
(2)Diabetology Unit, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Genoa, 6
Viale Benedetto XV, 16132, Genoa, Italy.
(3)First Clinic of Internal Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, University
of Genoa, 6 Viale Benedetto XV, 16132, Genoa, Italy.
(4)Center for Molecular Cardiology, University of Zürich, 12 Wagistrasse, 8952,
Schlieren, Switzerland.
(5)Emergency Department, Ospedale Policlinico San Martino, 10 Largo Benzi, 16132,
Genoa, Italy.
(6)Ospedale Policlinico San Martino, 10 Largo Benzi, 16132, Genoa, Italy.
(7)Centre of Excellence for Biomedical Research (CEBR), University of Genoa, 9
Viale Benedetto XV, 16132, Genoa, Italy.

AIMS: Hypoglycaemia represents a critical burden with clinical and social
consequences in the management of diabetes. Serum uric acid (SUA) has been
associated with cardiovascular diseases (CVD), but no conclusive findings are
available nowadays in patients suffering from hypoglycaemia. We investigated
whether SUA levels at the time of hypoglycaemia could predict all-cause mortality
after 1-year follow-up.
METHODS: In total, 219 patients admitted to the Emergency Department (ED) of
Ospedale Policlinico S. Martino of Genoa (Italy) have been enrolled between
January 2011 and December 2014. The primary endpoint of the study consisted in
determining whether SUA levels at the time of ED admission could predict the
occurrence of death after 1 year.
RESULTS: The majority of patients were diabetic, especially type 2. CVD and
chronic kidney disease were prevalent comorbidities. By a cut-off value obtained 
by the receiver operating characteristic curve analysis, a Kaplan-Meier analysis 
demonstrated that patients with SUA levels > 5.43 mg/dL were more prone to death 
after 1 year compared to those with lower SUA levels. The risk of death increased
with high SUA levels both in the univariate and the multivariate models including
estimated glomerular filtration rate, C-reactive protein, type of diabetes, and
age-adjusted Charlson comorbidity index.
CONCLUSIONS: SUA could be useful as a predictor of 1-year mortality in
hypoglycaemic patients, irrespective of severe comorbidities notably increasing
the risk of death in these frail patients.

DOI: 10.1007/s00592-017-1094-7 
PMID: 29327150  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


5. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2017 Jul 7;12(7):1100-1108. doi: 10.2215/CJN.12131116.
Epub 2017 Jun 2.

Factors Associated with Frailty and Its Trajectory among Patients on
Hemodialysis.

Johansen KL(1)(2)(3), Dalrymple LS(4), Delgado C(5)(2), Chertow GM(6), Segal
MR(3), Chiang J(2)(7), Grimes B(3), Kaysen GA(8)(9).

Author information: 
(1)Divisions of Nephrology and Kirsten.johansen@ucsf.edu.
(2)Nephrology and Endocrinology Sections, San Francisco Veterans Affairs Medical 
Center, San Francisco, California.
(3)Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University of California, San
Francisco, California.
(4)Fresenius Medical Care North America, Waltham, Massachusetts.
(5)Divisions of Nephrology and.
(6)Division of Nephrology, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford,
California; and.
(7)Endocrinology and.
(8)Division of Nephrology and.
(9)Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Medicine, University of California,
Davis, California.

BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVES: Frailty is common among patients on hemodialysis and
associated with adverse outcomes. However, little is known about changes in
frailty over time and the factors associated with those changes.
DESIGN, SETTING, PARTICIPANTS, & MEASUREMENTS: To address these questions, we
examined 762 participants in the A Cohort to Investigate the Value of
Exercise/Analyses Designed to Investigate the Paradox of Obesity and Survival in 
ESRD cohort study, among whom frailty was assessed at baseline and 12 and 24
months. We used ordinal generalized estimating equations analyses and modeled
frailty (on a scale from zero to five possible components) and death during
follow-up.
RESULTS: The mean frailty score at baseline was 1.9, and the distribution of
frailty scores was similar at each evaluation. However, most participants' scores
changed, with patients improving almost as often as worsening (overall change,
0.2 points per year; 95% confidence interval, 0.1 to 0.3). Hispanic ethnicity
(0.6 points per year; 95% confidence interval, 0.0 to 1.1) and diabetes (0.7
points per year; 95% confidence interval, 0.3 to 1.0) were associated with higher
frailty scores and higher serum albumin concentration with lower frailty scores
(-1.1 points per g/dl; 95% confidence interval, -1.5 to -0.7). In addition,
patients whose serum albumin increased over time were less likely to become
frail, with each 1-g/dl increase in albumin associated with a 0.4-point reduction
in frailty score (95% confidence interval, -0.80 to -0.05). To examine the
underpinnings of the association between serum albumin and frailty, we included
serum IL-6, normalized protein catabolic rate, and patient self-report of
hospitalization within the last year in a second model. Higher IL-6 and
hospitalization were statistically significantly associated with worse frailty at
any point and worsening frailty over time, whereas normalized protein catabolic
rate was not independently associated with frailty.
CONCLUSIONS: There was substantial year to year variability in frailty scores,
with approximately equal numbers of patients improving and worsening. Markers of 
inflammation and hospitalization were independently associated with worsening
frailty. Studies should examine whether interventions to address inflammation or 
posthospitalization rehabilitation can improve the trajectory of frailty.

Copyright © 2017 by the American Society of Nephrology.

DOI: 10.2215/CJN.12131116 
PMCID: PMC5498360
PMID: 28576906  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


6. Eur J Intern Med. 2017 Jul;42:16-23. doi: 10.1016/j.ejim.2017.04.018. Epub 2017
May 18.

Clinical management of iron deficiency anemia in adults: Systemic review on
advances in diagnosis and treatment.

De Franceschi L(1), Iolascon A(2), Taher A(3), Cappellini MD(4).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Medicine, Section of Internal Medicine, University of Verona,
Policlinico GB Rossi, AOUI, Verona, Italy.
(2)Dipartimento di Medicina Molecolare e Biotecnologie Mediche, Universita'
Federico II, Napoli, Italy; CEINGE, Advances Biotechnology, Napoli, Italy.
(3)Department of Internal Medicine, American University of Beirut Medical Center,
Beirut, Lebanon.
(4)Department of Internal Medicine, Universita' di Milano, Ca Granda Foundation, 
IRCCS, Milano, Italy. Electronic address: maria.cappellini@unimi.it.

Comment in
    Eur J Intern Med. 2018 Feb;48:e38.
    Eur J Intern Med. 2018 Feb;48:e39.

Global burden disease studies point out that one of the top cause-specific
anemias is iron deficiency (ID). Recent advances in knowledge of iron homeostasis
have shown that fragile patients are a new target population in which the
correction of ID might impact their morbidity, mortality and quality of life. We 
did a systematic review using specific search strategy, carried out the review of
PubMed database, Cochrane Database of systemic reviews and international
guidelines on diagnosis and clinical management of ID from 2010 to 2016. The
International guidelines were limited to those with peer-review process and
published in journal present in citation index database. The eligible studies
show that serum ferritin and transferrin saturation are the key tests in early
decision-making process to identify iron deficiency anemia (IDA). The clinician
has to carefully consider fragile and high-risk subset of patients such as elders
or individuals with chronic diseases (i.e chronic kidney disease, inflammatory
bowel disease, chronic heart failure). Treatment is based on iron
supplementation. Infusion route should be preferentially considered in frail
patients especially in the view of new iron available formulations. The available
evidences indicate that (i) recurrent IDA should always be investigated,
considering uncommon causes; (ii) IDA might worse the performance and the
clinical outcome of fragile and high-risk patients and require an intensive
treatment.

Copyright © 2017 European Federation of Internal Medicine. Published by Elsevier 
B.V. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.ejim.2017.04.018 
PMID: 28528999  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


7. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2017 Apr 1;32(4):591-597. doi: 10.1093/ndt/gfx021.

Considerations on glycaemic control in older and/or frail individuals with
diabetes and advanced kidney disease.

Panduru NM(1)(2)(3), Nistor I(4)(5), Groop PH(2)(3)(6)(7), Van Biesen W(4),
Farrington K(8)(9), Covic A(5).

Author information: 
(1)2nd Clinical Department, Diabetes, Nutrition and Metabolic Diseases Chair,
"Carol Davila" University of Medicine and Pharmacy, Bucharest, Romania.
(2)Folkhälsan Institute of Genetics, Folkhälsan Research Center, Biomedicum
Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland.
(3)Research Program Unit, Diabetes and Obesity, University of Helsinki, Helsinki,
Finland.
(4)ERBP, Ghent University Hospital, Ghent, Belgium.
(5)Nephrology Department, Gr. T. Popa University of Medicine and Pharmacy, Iasi, 
Romania.
(6)Abdominal Center Nephrology, University of Helsinki and Helsinki University
Hospital, Helsinki, Finland.
(7)Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia.
(8)Renal Unit, Lister Hospital, Stevenage, UK.
(9)Centre for Clinical and Health Services Research, University of Herts,
Hatfield, UK.

The increasing prevalence of chronic kidney disease (CKD) and diabetes over the
last decade has resulted in increasing numbers of frail older patients with a
combination of these conditions. Current treatment guidelines may not necessarily
be relevant for such patients, who are mostly excluded from the trials upon which
these recommendations are based. There is a paucity of data upon which to base
the management of older patients with CKD. Nearly all current guidelines
recommend less-tight glycaemic control for the older population, citing the lack 
of proven medium-term benefits and concerns about the high short-term risk of
hypoglycaemia. However, reports from large landmark trials have shown potential
benefits for both microvascular and macrovascular complications, though the
relevance of these findings to this specific population is uncertain. The trials 
have also highlighted potential alternative explanations for the hazards of
intensive glycaemic control. These include depression, low endogenous insulin
reserve, low body mass index and side effects of the medication. Over the last
few years, newer classes of hypoglycaemic drugs with a lower risk of
hypoglycaemia have emerged. This article aims to present a balanced view of
advantages and disadvantages of intense glycaemic control in this group of
patients, which we hope will help the clinician and patient to come to an
individualized management approach.

© The Author 2017. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of ERA-EDTA.
All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1093/ndt/gfx021 
PMID: 28340246  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


8. Panminerva Med. 2017 Jun;59(2):166-172. doi: 10.23736/S0031-0808.17.03293-1. Epub
2017 Jan 13.

Use of ACE inhibition and blood pressure management in deferring dialysis
initiation.

Del Vecchio L(1), Teatini U(2), Locatelli F(3).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Nephrology and Dialysis, A. Manzoni Hospital, ASST Lecco, Lecco,
Italy.
(2)Department of Nephrology and Dialysis, ASST Rhodense, Garbagnate Milanese,
Milan, Italy.
(3)Department of Nephrology and Dialysis, A. Manzoni Hospital, ASST Lecco, Lecco,
Italy - f.locatelli@asst-lecco.it.

Elevated blood pressure is one of the most significant risk factor for the
development of chronic kidney disease (CKD); its treatment is a milestone in CKD 
management. While it is accepted that a stricter blood pressure control is
indicated in patients with proteinuria or microalbuminuria, the exact degree of
blood pressure reduction to be obtained in CKD patients is still under debate.
Following more recent interpretation of old trials, a BP target for <140/90 mmHg 
is suggested for non-proteinuric CKD patients. In those with
microalbuminuria/proteinuria, the ideal blood pressure target should be ≤130/80
mmHg. Recently, the SPRINT trial put new emphasis on a stricter blood pressure
control, mainly from the cardiovascular point of view. The blockers of the
renin-angiotensin system (RAS) are recommended as first line treatment in all CKD
hypertensive patients with micro or macroalbuminuria either diabetics or not.
However, their nephroprotective efficacy is less relevant in non-proteinuric
patients. The dual RAS blockade was proposed as an additional option. Despite a
greater antiproteinuric effect, some large trials in patients at high
cardiovascular risk did not demonstrate significant advantage on hard endpoint.
Its use is now contraindicated in diabetic CKD patients. Given that RAS blockers 
can cause acute derangements in kidney function and hyperkalemia, caution is
needed with their use, especially in frail and old patients with cardiovascular
disease or in the presence of advanced CKD.

DOI: 10.23736/S0031-0808.17.03293-1 
PMID: 28090762  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


9. Am J Kidney Dis. 2017 Feb;69(2):228-236. doi: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2016.08.034. Epub
2016 Nov 22.

Frailty, Kidney Function, and Polypharmacy: The Atherosclerosis Risk in
Communities (ARIC) Study.

Ballew SH(1), Chen Y(2), Daya NR(2), Godino JG(3), Windham BG(4), McAdams-DeMarco
M(2), Coresh J(2), Selvin E(2), Grams ME(5).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Epidemiology, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health,
Baltimore, MD. Electronic address: sballew1@jhmi.edu.
(2)Department of Epidemiology, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health,
Baltimore, MD.
(3)Center for Wireless and Population Health Systems, Department of Family
Medicine and Public Health, University of California San Diego, San Diego, CA.
(4)Division of Geriatrics, Department of Medicine, University of Mississippi
Medical Center, Jackson, MS.
(5)Department of Epidemiology, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health,
Baltimore, MD; Division of Nephrology, Department of Medicine, Johns Hopkins
University, Baltimore, MD.

BACKGROUND: Frail individuals are at increased risk for poor outcomes, including 
adverse drug events. Kidney function is often compromised in frailty and is a key
consideration in medication choice and dosing; however, creatinine-based measures
of kidney function may be biased in frail individuals.
STUDY DESIGN: Observational study.
SETTING & PARTICIPANTS: 4,987 community-dwelling older men and women with
complete data who participated in visit 5 of the Atherosclerosis Risk in
Communities (ARIC) Study (2011-2013).
PREDICTORS: Kidney measures included glomerular filtration rate (GFR) estimated
using serum creatinine (eGFRcr) and serum cystatin C level (eGFRcys) and urine
albumin-creatinine ratio.
OUTCOME: Frailty, defined using established criteria of 3 or more frailty
characteristics (weight loss, slowness, exhaustion, weakness, and low physical
activity).
RESULTS: 341 (7%) participants were classified as frail, 1,475 (30%) had
eGFRcr<60mL/min/1.73m2, 2,480 (50%) had eGFRcys<60mL/min/1.73m2, and 1,006 (20%) 
had albuminuria with albumin excretion ≥ 30mg/g. Among frail participants,
prevalences of eGFRcr and eGFRcys<60mL/min/1.73m2 were 45% and 77%, respectively.
Adjusted for covariates, frailty showed a moderate association with eGFRcr and a 
strong association with eGFRcys and albumin-creatinine ratio. Frail individuals
with eGFRcr of 60 to <75mL/min/1.73m2 were frequently reclassified to lower eGFR 
categories using eGFRcys (49% to 45-<60, 32% to 30-<45, and 3%
to <30mL/min/1.73m2). Hyperpolypharmacy (taking ≥10 classes of medications) was
more common in frail individuals (54% vs 38% of nonfrail), including classes
requiring kidney clearance (eg, digoxin) and associated with falls and subsequent
complications (eg, hypnotic/sedatives and anticoagulants).
LIMITATIONS: Cross-sectional study design.
CONCLUSIONS: Frail individuals had a high prevalence of reduced kidney function, 
with large discrepancies when reduced kidney function was classified by eGFRcys
versus eGFRcr. Given the substantial medication burden and uncertainty in chronic
kidney disease classification, confirmation of kidney function with alternative
biomarkers may be warranted to ensure careful prescribing practices in this
vulnerable population.

Copyright © 2016 National Kidney Foundation, Inc. Published by Elsevier Inc. All 
rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2016.08.034 
PMCID: PMC5263025
PMID: 27884475  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


10. Cien Saude Colet. 2016 Nov;21(11):3493-3498. doi:
10.1590/1413-812320152111.18222015.

[Factors associated with the frailty of elderly people with chronic kidney
disease on hemodialysis].

[Article in Portuguese]

Gesualdo GD(1), Zazzetta MS(2), Say KG(2), Orlandi FS(2).

Author information: 
(1)Programa de Pós-Graduação em Enfermagem Fundamental, Escola de Enfermagem de
Ribeirão Preto, Universidade de São Paulo. Av. Bandeirantes 3900, Bairro Monte
Alegre. 14049-900 Ribeirão Preto SP Brasil. gabrieladutra.gesualdo@yahoo.com.br.
(2)Departamento de Gerontologia, UFSCar. São Carlos SP Brasil.

The scope of this article is to identify sociodemographic and clinical factors
associated with the frailty of elderly people with chronic kidney disease on
hemodialysis. This involved a correlational, cross-sectional study conducted in a
dialysis center in the state of São Paulo. The sample consisted of 60
participants. The Participant Characterization Instrument was used for extracting
sociodemographic and clinical data and the Edmonton Frail Scale was used to
evaluate the level of frailty. Multivariate logistic regression was used to
identify the factors associated with frailty. The mean age of the 60 patients
included was 71.1 (± 6.9) years, predominantly male (70%), of which 36.7% were
classified as frail. With respect to the factors associated with frailty among
the variables of gender, age, self-reported skin color, schooling, monthly per
capita income, hemodialysis time, number of associated diseases, falls in the
year, hematocrit level, parathyroid hormone and use of calcitriol, it was found
that only the monthly per capita income was significantly associated with frailty
(OR = 0.44; 95% CI 0.1-0.9; p = 0.04). There was an association between frailty
and income, showing that the elderly most at risk of frailty were those with
lower income.

DOI: 10.1590/1413-812320152111.18222015 
PMID: 27828582  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


11. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2016 Nov;31(11):1796-1802. Epub 2015 Sep 28.

Should chronic metabolic acidosis be treated in older people with chronic kidney 
disease?

Witham MD(1), Lamb EJ(2).

Author information: 
(1)Ageing and Health, School of Medicine, University of Dundee, Dundee, UK.
(2)Clinical Biochemistry, Department of Laboratory Medicine, East Kent Hospitals 
University NHS Foundation Trust, Canterbury, Kent, UK.

Metabolic acidosis is common in advanced chronic kidney disease and has been
associated with a range of physiological derangements of importance to the health
of older people. These include associations with skeletal muscle weakness,
cardiovascular risk factors, and bone and mineral disorders that may lead to
fragility fractures. Although metabolic acidosis is associated with accelerated
decline in kidney function, end-stage renal failure is a much less common outcome
in older, frail patients than cardiovascular death. Correction of metabolic
acidosis using bicarbonate therapy is commonly employed, but the existing
evidence is insufficient to know whether such therapy is of net benefit to older 
people. Bicarbonate is bulky and awkward to take, may impose additional sodium
load with effects on fluid retention and blood pressure, and may cause
gastrointestinal side effects. Trial data to date suggest potential benefits of
bicarbonate therapy on progression of renal disease and nutrition, but trials
have not as yet been published examining the effect of bicarbonate therapy across
a range of domains relevant to the health of older people. Fortunately, a number 
of trials are now underway that should allow us to ascertain whether bicarbonate 
therapy can improve physical function, quality of life, and vascular, bone and
kidney health in older people, and hence decide whether any benefits seen
outweigh adverse effects and additional treatment burden in this vulnerable group
of patients.

© The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of ERA-EDTA.
All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1093/ndt/gfv344 
PMID: 26420895  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


12. J Nephrol. 2016 Dec;29(6):783-789. Epub 2016 Jan 22.

Metformin associated lactic acidosis (MALA): clinical profiling and management.

Moioli A(1)(2), Maresca B(1)(2), Manzione A(1)(2), Napoletano AM(3), Coclite
D(3), Pirozzi N(1)(2), Punzo G(1)(2), Menè P(4)(5)(6).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Clinical and Molecular Medicine, University of Rome "La
Sapienza", Rome, Italy.
(2)Chair and Division of Nephrology, Sant'Andrea University Hospital, Rome,
Italy.
(3)Istituto Superiore di Sanità, Rome, Italy.
(4)Department of Clinical and Molecular Medicine, University of Rome "La
Sapienza", Rome, Italy. paolo.mene@uniroma1.it.
(5)Chair and Division of Nephrology, Sant'Andrea University Hospital, Rome,
Italy. paolo.mene@uniroma1.it.
(6)UOC Nefrologia, A.O. Sant'Andrea, Via di Grottarossa 1035-1039, 00189, Rome,
Italy. paolo.mene@uniroma1.it.

Metformin (MF) accumulation during acute kidney injury is associated with high
anion gap lactic acidosis type B (MF-associated lactic acidosis, MALA), a serious
medical condition leading to high mortality. Despite dose adjustment for renal
failure, diabetic patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD) stage III-IV are at 
risk for rapid decline in renal function by whatever reason, so that MF toxicity 
might arise if the drug is not timely withdrawn. Sixteen consecutive patients
were admitted to our Hospital's Emergency Department with clinical findings
consistent with MALA. Fifteen had prior history of CKD, 60 % of them with GFR
between 30 and 60 ml/min. Of these, 5 required mechanical ventilation and
cardiovascular support; 3 promptly recovered renal function after rehydration,
whereas 10 (62 %) required continuous veno-venous renal replacement treatment.
SOFA and SAPS II scores were significantly related to the degree of lactic
acidosis. In addition, lactate levels were relevant to therapeutic choices, since
they were higher in dialyzed patients than in those on conservative treatment
(11.92 mmol/l vs 5.7 mmol/l, p = 0.03). The overall death rate has been 31 %,
with poorer prognosis for worse acidemia, as serum pH was significantly lower in 
non-survivors (pH 6.96 vs 7.16, p > 0.04). Our own data and a review of the
literature suggest that aged, hemodynamically frail patients, with several
comorbidities and CKD, are at greater risk of MALA, despite MF dosage adjustment.
Moreover, renal replacement therapy rather than simple acidosis correction by
administration of alkali seems the treatment of choice, based on eventual renal
recovery and overall outcome.

DOI: 10.1007/s40620-016-0267-8 
PMID: 26800971  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


13. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2016 Oct;64(10):2154-2158. doi: 10.1111/jgs.14262. Epub 2016
Jul 5.

Incorporating Geriatric Assessment into a Nephrology Clinic: Preliminary Data
from Two Models of Care.

Hall RK(1)(2)(3), Haines C(4), Gorbatkin SM(5)(6), Schlanger L(5)(6), Shaban
H(7), Schell JO(8), Gurley SB(4)(7), Colón-Emeric CS(9)(7), Bowling CB(6)(10).

Author information: 
(1)Geriatric Research, Education and Clinical Center, Durham Veterans Affairs
Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina. rasheeda.stephens@dm.duke.edu.
(2)Renal Section, Durham Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina.
rasheeda.stephens@dm.duke.edu.
(3)Department of Medicine, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, North
Carolina. rasheeda.stephens@dm.duke.edu.
(4)Renal Section, Durham Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina.
(5)Nephrology Service, Atlanta Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Decatur, Georgia.
(6)Department of Medicine, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia.
(7)Department of Medicine, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, North
Carolina.
(8)Department of Medicine, University of Pittsburgh Medical Center, Pittsburgh,
Pennsylvania.
(9)Geriatric Research, Education and Clinical Center, Durham Veterans Affairs
Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina.
(10)Geriatric Research, Education and Clinical Center, Birmingham/Atlanta
Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Decatur, Georgia.

Comment in
    J Am Geriatr Soc. 2017 Apr;65(4):878-880.
    J Am Geriatr Soc. 2017 Apr;65(4):880.

Older adults with advanced chronic kidney disease (CKD) experience functional
impairment that can complicate CKD management. Failure to recognize functional
impairment may put these individuals at risk of further functional decline,
nursing home placement, and missed opportunities for timely goals-of-care
conversations. Routine geriatric assessment could be a useful tool for
identifying older adults with CKD who are at risk of functional decline and
provide contextual information to guide clinical decision-making. Two innovative 
programs were implemented in the Veterans Health Administration that incorporate 
geriatric assessment into a nephrology visit. In one program, a geriatrician
embedded in a nephrology clinic used standardized geriatric assessment tools with
individuals with CKD aged 70 and older (Comprehensive Geriatric Assessment for
CKD) (CGA-4-CKD). In the second program, a nephrology clinic used comprehensive
appointments for individuals aged 75 and older to conduct geriatric assessments
and CKD care (Renal Silver). Data on 68 veterans who had geriatric assessments
through these programs between November 2013 and May 2015 are reported. In
CGA-4-CKD, difficulty with one or more activities of daily living (ADLs), history
of falls, and cognitive impairment were each found in 27.3% of participants. ADL 
difficulty was found in 65.7%, falls in 28.6%, and cognitive impairment in 51.6% 
of participants in Renal Silver. Geriatric assessment guided care processes in
45.4% (n = 15) of veterans in the CGA-4-CKD program and 37.1% (n = 13) of those
in Renal Silver. Findings suggest there is a significant burden of functional
impairment in older adults with CKD. Knowledge of this impairment is applicable
to CKD management.

© 2016, Copyright the Authors Journal compilation © 2016, The American Geriatrics
Society.

DOI: 10.1111/jgs.14262 
PMCID: PMC5073016
PMID: 27377350  [Indexed for MEDLINE]

Conflict of interest statement: Conflict of Interest: The editor in chief has
reviewed the conflict of interest checklist provided by the authors and has
determined that the authors have no financial or any other kind of personal
conflicts with this paper. Rasheeda K. Hall, Carol Haines, Steven M. Gorbatkin,
Lynn Schlanger, Hesham Shaban, Jane O. Schell, Susan B. Gurley, Cathleen S.
Colón-Emeric, C. Barrett Bowling


14. Geriatr Gerontol Int. 2017 Oct;17(10):1527-1533. doi: 10.1111/ggi.12910. Epub
2016 Sep 27.

Relationship between chronic kidney disease with diabetes or hypertension and
frailty in community-dwelling Japanese older adults.

Lee S(1), Lee S(1), Harada K(1)(2), Bae S(1), Makizako H(1), Doi T(1),
Tsutsumimoto K(1), Hotta R(1), Nakakubo S(1), Park H(1)(3), Suzuki T(1)(4),
Shimada H(1).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Preventive Gerontology, Center for Gerontology and Social
Science, National Center for Geriatrics and Gerontology, Obu, Japan.
(2)Graduate School of Human Development and Environment, Kobe University, Japan.
(3)Department of Health Care and Science, Dong-A University, Busan, Korea.
(4)Institute for Aging and Development, J.F. Oberlin University, Tokyo, Japan.

AIM: The aim of the present study was to evaluate the relationship between kidney
function with concomitant diabetes or hypertension and frailty in
community-dwelling Japanese older adults.
METHODS: The participants were 9606 residents (community-dwelling Japanese older 
adults) who completed baseline assessments. The estimated glomerular filtration
rate (mL/min/1.73 m2 ) was determined according to the serum creatinine level,
and participants were classified into four mutually exclusive categories: ≥60.0
(normal range), 45.0-59.9, 30.0-44.9 and <30.0 mL/min/1.73 m2 . Frailty status
was defined using five criteria as described by Fried: slow gait speed, muscle
weakness, low physical activity, exhaustion and unintentional weight loss.
Participants who met three, four or five criteria satisfied the definition of
having frailty. Multivariate logistic regression was used to examine the
relationships between estimated glomerular filtration rate and frailty.
RESULTS: After multivariate adjustment, participants with lower kidney function
(estimated glomerular filtration rate <30.0 mL/min/1.73 m2 ) were more frail
(odds ratio [OR] 1.90, 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.01-3.59). In addition,
individuals with a history of diabetes (OR 2.76, 95% CI 1.21-8.24) or
hypertension (OR 2.53, 95% CI 1.45-5.12) showed a significantly increased risk of
frailty in the lower kidney function group, regardless of multivariate controls. 
Furthermore, the analyses showed an even greater increase in the risk of frailty 
in patients with a history of both diabetes and hypertension (OR 3.67, 95% CI
1.13-14.1) CONCLUSIONS: A lower level of kidney function was associated with a
higher risk of frailty in community-dwelling Japanese older adults. Geriatr
Gerontol Int 2017; 17: 1527-1533.

© 2016 Japan Geriatrics Society.

DOI: 10.1111/ggi.12910 
PMID: 27670391  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


15. Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg. 2016 Dec;23(6):985-987. Epub 2016 Aug 19.

Surgical management without resection of the oesophagus for aorto-oesophageal
fistula secondary to aortic arch aneurysm rupture.

Omura A(1), Yoshida M(2), Koda Y(2), Mukohara N(2).

Author information: 
(1)Division of Cardiovascular Surgery, Hyogo Brain and Heart Center at Himeji,
Himeji, Japan atchun1029@gmail.com.
(2)Division of Cardiovascular Surgery, Hyogo Brain and Heart Center at Himeji,
Himeji, Japan.

Comment in
    Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg. 2016 Dec;23 (6):987.

A 79-year-old moderately frail man with a history of graft replacement for
descending thoracic aortic aneurysm and chronic kidney disease presented with the
onset of haemoptysis. Computed tomography demonstrated aorto-oesophageal fistula 
secondary to aortic arch aneurysm rupture. Emergency surgery was performed
through a median sternotomy. Cardiopulmonary bypass was established via femoral
artery inflow and bicaval venous drainage. After establishing circulatory arrest,
the aortic arch was excised. Resection of the aortic aneurysm and debridement
were performed during antegrade cerebral perfusion and lower body perfusion from 
femoral artery inflow using balloon occlusion of the previous graft. Aortic arch 
graft replacement with concomitant debridement of mediastinal tissue and direct
repair of oesophageal perforation comprised a first-stage operation. Forty hours 
later, abundant irrigation of warm normal saline around the mediastinal cavity
and the omental flap covering the graft and the repair site of the oesophagus
comprised the second-stage operation. Although the postoperative course was
complicated, the patient resumed oral intake within 2 months after the initial
operation. Serial computed tomography and oesophageal endoscopy showed good
healing of the aorto-oesophageal fistula. There were no clinical manifestations
or imaging findings of deep mediastinal infection throughout the postoperative
course.

© The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European
Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1093/icvts/ivw239 
PMID: 27543651  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


16. Nefrologia. 2016 Nov - Dec;36(6):609-615. doi: 10.1016/j.nefro.2016.03.020. Epub 
2016 May 27.

Frailty in elderly people with chronic kidney disease.

[Article in English, Spanish]

Portilla Franco ME(1), Tornero Molina F(2), Gil Gregorio P(3).

Author information: 
(1)Servicio de Geriatría, Hospital Clínico San Carlos, Madrid, España. Electronic
address: maeportilla@gmail.com.
(2)Servicio de Nefrología, Hospital Clínico San Carlos, Madrid, España.
(3)Servicio de Geriatría, Hospital Clínico San Carlos, Madrid, España.

In recent years, the concept of frailty as a "state of pre-disability" has been
widely accepted by those involved in the care of the elderly. Its importance lies
not only in its high prevalence - more than 25% in people over 85 years of age - 
but it is also considered an independent risk factor of disability,
institutionalisation and mortality amongst the elderly. The study of renal
function is relevant in patients with major comorbidities. Studies have shown a
significant association between chronic kidney disease and the development of
adverse clinical outcomes such as heart disease, heart failure, end-stage renal
disease, increased susceptibility to infections and greater functional
impairment. Frailty can be reversed, which is why a study of frailty in patients 
with chronic kidney disease is of particular interest. This article aims to
describe the association between ageing, frailty and chronic kidney disease in
light of the most recent and relevant scientific publications.

Copyright Â© 2016 Sociedad Española de Nefrología. Published by Elsevier España, 
S.L.U. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.nefro.2016.03.020 
PMID: 27242263  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


17. Rev Med Liege. 2015 Dec;70(12):593-9.

[How I TREAT ... THE ROLE OF DPP-4 INHIBITORS (GLIPTINS) IN THE TREATMENT OF TYPE
2 DIABETES].

[Article in French]

Scheen AJ.

Dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP-4) inhibitors (gliptins) are more and more prominent 
medications in the management of type 2 diabetes (T2D), with five molecules
commercialized and as many fixed-dose combinations with metformin. After failure 
of metformin monotherapy, gliptins compete with old medications such as
sulphonylureas, on the one hand, or with new oral antidiabetic agents such as
inhibitors of renal sodium-glucose cotransporters type 2 (SGLT2) (gliflozines),
on the other hand. Another alternative is the use of an incretin mimetic (agonist
of glucagon-like peptide-1 receptors, to be injected subcutaneously) rather than 
an incretin enhancer such as a gliptin, before considering insulin therapy. This 
article analyses the arguments in favour of DPP-4 inhibitors. We will mainly
consider the use of gliptins in patients with recently diagnosed T2D, in elderly 
and frail patients and in those with chronic kidney disease. To illustrate the
discussion, we will analyze the results of both interventional and observational 
studies with vildagliptin. Obviously, these various groups of patients represent 
a large proportion of T2D population.


PMID: 26867302  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


18. BMC Nephrol. 2015 Oct 29;16:176. doi: 10.1186/s12882-015-0173-7.

Renal disease and accidental falls: a review of published evidence.

López-Soto PJ(1), De Giorgi A(2)(3), Senno E(4), Tiseo R(5), Ferraresi A(6),
Canella C(7), Rodríguez-Borrego MA(8), Manfredini R(9)(10), Fabbian F(11)(12).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Nursing, The Maimonides Institute for Biomedical Research in
Cordoba, University of Córdoba, University Hospital Reina Sofía of Córdoba,
Córdoba, Spain. pablolopezsoto90@gmail.com.
(2)Clinica Medica, Department of Medical Science, University of Ferrara, Ferrara,
Italy. degiogialfredo@libero.it.
(3)Department of Medicine, Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria (AOU) of Ferrara,
Ferrara, Italy. degiogialfredo@libero.it.
(4)Clinica Medica, Department of Medical Science, University of Ferrara, Ferrara,
Italy. elisa.senno@student.unife.it.
(5)Department of Medicine, Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria (AOU) of Ferrara,
Ferrara, Italy. r.tiseo@libero.it.
(6)U.O. Formazione e Aggiornamento, Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria (AOU) of
Ferrara, Ferrara, Italy. a.ferraresi@ospfe.it.
(7)U.O. Formazione e Aggiornamento, Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria (AOU) of
Ferrara, Ferrara, Italy. c.canella@ospfe.it.
(8)Department of Nursing, The Maimonides Institute for Biomedical Research in
Cordoba, University of Córdoba, University Hospital Reina Sofía of Córdoba,
Córdoba, Spain. en1robom@uco.es.
(9)Clinica Medica, Department of Medical Science, University of Ferrara, Ferrara,
Italy. roberto.manfredini@unife.it.
(10)Department of Medicine, Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria (AOU) of Ferrara,
Ferrara, Italy. roberto.manfredini@unife.it.
(11)Clinica Medica, Department of Medical Science, University of Ferrara,
Ferrara, Italy. f.fabbian@ospfe.it.
(12)Department of Medicine, Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria (AOU) of Ferrara,
Ferrara, Italy. f.fabbian@ospfe.it.

BACKGROUND: The pathogenesis of falling is complex, and identification of risk
factors may be essential for prevention. The relationship between renal disease
and falls is unclear, and the goal of this study was to collect the available
evidence and investigate the relationship between accidental falls and renal
dysfunction.
METHODS: Electronic searches were performed in the MEDLINE, Scopus, Ovid SP and
Web of Science databases to identify the appropriate literature. The themes used 
were: falls (combined in the title/abstract fall or falls or falling or faller*
or fallen or slip* or trip* or (MeSH) accidental falls) and renal insufficiency
(chronic or renal insufficiency or kidney diseases combined in title/abstract
renal disease* or kidney disease* or renal insufficiency or kidney insufficiency 
or kidney failure or renal failure or MeSH renal insufficiency, chronic or renal 
insufficiency or kidney diseases). The incidence, risk factors, complications,
and characteristics of the falls were analyzed.
RESULTS: Eight prospective cohorts including five cross-sectional studies, and
one case-control study were identified. No randomized controlled studies were
found. The incidence of falls in chronic kidney disease patients ranged between
1.18 and 1.60 fall/patient year. These were frequent in frail older adults on
hemodialysis treatment. Falling relapses in the same group of patients caused
serious consequences. Data on pre-end stage renal disease (ESRD) were scarce.
CONCLUSIONS: The risk of falling appears to be common in patients with renal
dysfunction especially in older adults undergoing hemodialysis. On the other
hand, we could not find any conclusive data on pre-ESRD patients.

DOI: 10.1186/s12882-015-0173-7 
PMCID: PMC4625452
PMID: 26510510  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


19. Clin Med (Lond). 2015 Oct;15(5):465-7. doi: 10.7861/clinmedicine.15-5-465.

Diabetes in older people.

Bennett K(1).

Author information: 
(1)University Hospital Aintree, Liverpool, UK.

The management of diabetes in older people is often challenging and poorly
researched. The prevalence of cognitive impairment, chronic kidney disease and
other co-existing comorbidities increase with age and have a significant impact
on glycaemic control targets and treatment options. This conference examined
current clinical practice, highlighted differences in the management of diabetes 
in the older person and suggested potential areas of future research.

© Royal College of Physicians 2015. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.7861/clinmedicine.15-5-465 
PMCID: PMC4953233
PMID: 26430187  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


20. Int Urol Nephrol. 2015 Nov;47(11):1801-7. doi: 10.1007/s11255-015-1112-z. Epub
2015 Sep 28.

Frailty phenotype and chronic kidney disease: a review of the literature.

Musso CG(1), Jauregui JR(2), Macías Núñez JF(3).

Author information: 
(1)Ageing Biology Unit, Hospital Italiano de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires,
Argentina. carlos.musso@hospitalitaliano.org.ar.
(2)Ageing Biology Unit, Hospital Italiano de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires,
Argentina.
(3)Nephrology Division, Hospital Universitario de Salamanca, Salamanca, Spain.

Frailty is a construct originally coined by gerontologists to describe cumulative
declines across multiple physiological systems that occur with aging and lead
individuals to a state of diminished physiological reserve and increased
vulnerability to stressors. Fried et al. provided a standardized definition for
frailty, and they created the concept of frailty phenotype which incorporates
disturbances across interrelated domains (shrinking, weakness, poor endurance and
energy, slowness, and low physical activity level) to indentify old people who
are at risk of disability, falls, institutionalization, hospitalization, and
premature death. Some authors consider the presence of lean mass reduction
(sarcopenia) as part of the frailty phenotype. The frailty status has been
documented in 7 % of elderly population and 14 % of not requiring dialysis CKD
adult patients. Sarcopenia increases progressively along with loss of renal
function in CKD patients and is high in dialysis population. It has been
documented that prevalence of frailty in hemodialysis adult patients is around 42
% (35 % in young and 50 % in elderly), having a 2.60-fold higher risk of
mortality and 1.43-fold higher number of hospitalization, independent of age,
comorbidity, and disability. The Clinical Frailty Scale is the simplest and
clinically useful and validated tool for doing a frailty phenotype, while the
diagnosis of sarcopenia is based on muscle mass assessment by body imaging
techniques, bioimpedance analysis, and muscle strength evaluated with a handheld 
dynamometer. Frailty treatment can be based on different strategies, such as
exercise, nutritional interventions, drugs, vitamins, and antioxidant agents.
Finally, palliative care is a very important alternative for very frail and sick 
patients. In conclusion, since the diagnosis and treatment of frailty and
sarcopenia is crucial in geriatrics and all CKD patients, it would be very
important to incorporate these evaluations in pre-dialysis, peritoneal dialysis, 
hemodialysis, and kidney transplant patients in order to detect and consequently 
treat the frailty phenotype in these groups.

DOI: 10.1007/s11255-015-1112-z 
PMID: 26411428  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


21. BMC Nephrol. 2015 Sep 23;16:157. doi: 10.1186/s12882-015-0150-1.

Association of frailty with endothelial dysfunction and its possible impact on
negative outcomes in Brazilian predialysis patients with chronic kidney disease.

Mansur HN(1)(2), Lovisi JC(3), Colugnati FA(3), Raposo NR(3), Fernandes NM(3),
Bastos MG(4).

Author information: 
(1)IMEPEN Foundation, Federal University of Juiz de Fora, Juiz de Fora, Brazil.
hnmansur@gmail.com.
(2)Academic Centre of Vitoria, Federal University of Pernambuco, Vitória de Santo
Antão, Pernambuco, Brazil. hnmansur@gmail.com.
(3)IMEPEN Foundation, Federal University of Juiz de Fora, Juiz de Fora, Brazil.
(4)Federal University of Juiz de Fora, José Lourenço Kelmer Street, 1300, Juiz de
Fora, Minas Gerais, Brazil. marcusbastos7@gmail.com.

BACKGROUND: Frailty is a state of physiological vulnerability common in the
elderly. It is more predominant in patients with Chronic Kidney Disease in
comparison to healthy subjects, which can also be diagnosed in non-elderly
individuals and be associated with innumerous causes such as muscle strength,
body composition and inflammation. The association between frailty and
endothelial function, as well as the association between frailty and the combined
outcome of mortality multiple cause and start of renal replace therapy were
assessed.
METHODS: In the initial analysis, sixty-one predialysis patients with Chronic
Kidney Disease stages were evaluated and included in this study. Due to patient
drop-out during follow-up, fifty-seven patients were subsequently re-evaluated 12
months later. The diagnosis of frailty was based on the Johansen et al. (J Am Soc
Nephrol 18(11):2960-67, 2007) criteria. The groups were divided into Non-frail
and Frail. Sociodemographic, inflammatory markers (IL-6, TNF-?, CRP-us),
endothelial dysfunction (flow-mediated vasodilatation - FMD), body composition
(DXA) and the 25-hidroxi-vitamin D parameters were analyzed.
RESULTS: The average age of the patients used in the study was 64.9 ± 10.3 years 
old. The predominance of frailty was 42.6%, of which 46% were non-elderly. After 
some adjustments, frailty was associated with gender (OR = 11.32; IC 95% = 2.30
to 55.67), advanced age (OR = 4.07; IC 95% = 1.02 to 16.20), obesity (OR = 6.63; 
IC 95% = 0.82 to 11.44) and endothelial dysfunction (OR = 3.86; IC 95% = 1.00 to 
14.88). The ratio of the incidence of frail subjects to the variable outcome was 
2.5 (CI 95%, 1.04 to 6.50).
CONCLUSIONS: Although an observational study does not allow one to determine the 
casual relation between frailty and endothelial dysfunction, we conclude that
frailty was predominant in our sample of Brazilian patients with chronic kidney
disease on predialysis, even in elderly individuals. This was linked to either
worse endothelial function or mortality.

DOI: 10.1186/s12882-015-0150-1 
PMCID: PMC4579818
PMID: 26395776  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


22. Australas J Ageing. 2015 Sep;34(3):E9-12. doi: 10.1111/ajag.12231.

Feasibility and construct validity of a Frailty index for patients with chronic
kidney disease.

Hubbard RE(1), Peel NM(1), Smith M(2)(3), Dawson B(3), Lambat Z(3), Bak M(3),
Best J(4), Johnson DW(4).

Author information: 
(1)Centre for Research in Geriatric Medicine, The University of Queensland,
Brisbane, Queensland, Australia.
(2)Ochsner Medical School, New Orleans, Louisiana, USA.
(3)School of Medicine, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Queensland,
Australia.
(4)Department of Nephrology, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Queensland, 
Australia.

AIM: To determine whether the frailty status of patients with chronic kidney
disease (CKD) can be measured using a Frailty index (FI).
METHODS: One hundred and eleven attending a nephrology clinic were approached to 
complete a one-page questionnaire evaluating cognitive, psychological and
functional status. Data were coded as deficits, summed and divided by the total
number of deficits considered, to derive an FI-CKD.
RESULTS: One hundred and ten (mean age 65.2 years) agreed to participate and
assessments took approximately 10 minutes to complete. Mean FI-CKD was 0.25 (SD
0.12). The FI-CKD increased with age at 3% per year, correlated with a modified
Fried phenotype (P < 0.001) and increased significantly across CKD stages (P =
0.04).
CONCLUSIONS: The FI-CKD is feasible in the outpatient setting and has good
construct validity. The greater granularity of a continuous measure has the
potential to inform decision-making regarding appropriate interventions for
patients at the 'frail' end of the health spectrum.

© 2015 AJA Inc.

DOI: 10.1111/ajag.12231 
PMID: 26337415  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


23. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2015 May 29;13:70. doi: 10.1186/s12955-015-0270-0.

Influence of frailty on health-related quality of life in pre-dialysis patients
with chronic kidney disease in Korea: a cross-sectional study.

Lee SJ(1), Son H(2), Shin SK(3).

Author information: 
(1)Red Cross College of Nursing, Chung-Ang University, 84 Heukseok-ro,
Dongjak-gu, Seoul, South Korea. lsj1109@cau.ac.kr.
(2)Red Cross College of Nursing, Chung-Ang University, 84 Heukseok-ro,
Dongjak-gu, Seoul, South Korea. hson@cau.ac.kr.
(3)National Health Insurance Cooperation Ilsan Hospital Clinical Professor,
Yonsei University Medical College, Seoul, South Korea.

BACKGROUND: Chronic kidney disease (CKD) is a progressive and lifelong condition 
with multiple medical comorbidities. Patients with CKD experience frailty more
frequently and have lower health-related quality of life than do those with other
chronic diseases. The purpose of this study was to examine the prevalence of
frailty and investigate the contribution of frailty to quality of life in
pre-dialysis CKD patients in Korea.
METHODS: Using a cross-sectional survey design, data were collected at an
outpatient CKD clinic in a general hospital in Korea. The frailty criterion was
modified from previous studies. The Short Form-36 Health Survey version 2 was
used to measure physical and mental component summary scores. Data were analyzed 
using chi-square, t-tests, and hierarchical linear regression.
RESULTS: Of the 168 CKD patients, 63 (37.5 %) were frail. Frail patients were
significantly older and had lower physical and mental quality of life than those 
who were non-frail. In hierarchical regression evaluating the influence of
frailty on physical and mental quality of life, the initial model was
significantly improved when frailty was included. Frail patients had lower
physical and mental quality of life.
CONCLUSIONS: Frailty affected both physical and mental quality of life in
pre-dialysis patients with CKD. More attention should be paid to the potential
role of early detection and prevention of frailty to improve patients' quality of
life.

DOI: 10.1186/s12955-015-0270-0 
PMCID: PMC4460686
PMID: 26021987  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


24. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2016 Jul;31(7):1070-7. doi: 10.1093/ndt/gfv122. Epub
2015 Apr 24.

Muscle wasting in end-stage renal disease promulgates premature death:
established, emerging and potential novel treatment strategies.

Stenvinkel P(1), Carrero JJ(1), von Walden F(2), Ikizler TA(3), Nader GA(4).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Renal Medicine, CLINTEC, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm,
Sweden.
(2)Department of Women's and Children's Health, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm,
Sweden.
(3)Division of Nephrology, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, USA.
(4)Department of Kinesiology, The Pennsylvania State University, University Park,
USA.

Muscle wasting (or sarcopenia) is a common feature of the uremic phenotype and
predisposes this vulnerable patient population to increased risk of comorbid
complications, poor quality of life, frailty and premature death. The old age of 
dialysis patients is in addition a likely contributor to loss of muscle mass. As 
recent evidence suggests that assessment of muscle strength (i.e. function) is a 
better predictor of outcome and comorbidities than muscle mass, this opens new
screening, assessment and therapeutic opportunities. Among established treatment 
strategies, the benefit of resistance exercise and endurance training are
increasingly recognized among nephrologists as being effective and should be
promoted in sedentary chronic kidney disease patients. Testosterone and growth
hormone replacement appear as the most promising among emerging treatments
strategies for muscle wasting. As treatment of muscle wasting is difficult and
seldom successful in this often old, frail, sedentary and exercise-hesitant
patient group, novel treatment strategies are urgently needed. In this review, we
summarize recent studies on stimulation of mitochondrial biogenesis, myogenic
stem (satellite) cells and manipulation of transforming growth factor family
members, all of which hold promise for more effective therapies to target muscle 
mass loss and function in the future.

© The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of ERA-EDTA.
All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1093/ndt/gfv122 
PMID: 25910496  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


25. South Med J. 2015 Feb;108(2):91-6. doi: 10.14423/SMJ.0000000000000235.

Use of sodium-glucose cotransporter type 2 inhibitors in older adults with type 2
diabetes mellitus.

Mikhail N(1).

Author information: 
(1)From the Department of Medicine, Division of Endocrinology, Olive-View UCLA
Medical Center, Sylmar, California.

Sodium-glucose cotransporter type 2 (SGLT2) inhibitors such as canagliflozin and 
dapagliflozin have been approved for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus. A
PubMed search was conducted of the literature from April 1996 to August 2014 to
identify all human studies related to SGLT2 inhibitors. Pertinent guidelines of
experts and the prescribing information for canagliflozin and dapagliflozin are
reviewed. SGLT2 inhibitors may be used as an add-on therapy in select and
relatively healthy older patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus who are
overweight and have uncontrolled hypertension. These medications should be
avoided in patients who are frail, who have chronic kidney disease, and in
conjunction with insulin or sulfonylureas.

DOI: 10.14423/SMJ.0000000000000235 
PMID: 25688893  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


26. Geriatr Nurs. 2015 Mar-Apr;36(2):136-41. doi: 10.1016/j.gerinurse.2014.12.012.
Epub 2015 Jan 20.

Chronic kidney disease and recurrent falls in nursing home residents: a
retrospective cohort study.

Hall RK(1), Landerman LR(2), O'Hare AM(3), Anderson RA(4), Colón-Emeric CS(5).

Author information: 
(1)Duke University Medical Center, Division of Nephrology, Department of
Medicine, Box DUMC 2747, 2424 Erwin Road Suite 605, Durham, NC 27710, USA; Durham
VA Geriatric Research, Education and Clinical Center, 508 Fulton Street, Durham, 
NC 27705, USA. Electronic address: rasheeda.stephens@dm.duke.edu.
(2)Duke University Medical Center, Division of Geriatrics, Department of
Medicine, Box DUMC 3003, Durham, NC 27710, USA; Duke University School of
Nursing, DUMC Box 3322, 307 Trent Drive, Durham, NC 27710, USA.
(3)VA Puget Sound Healthcare System, Department of Medicine and HSR&D Center of
Excellence, 1660 S. Columbian Way, Seattle, WA 98108, USA; University of
Washington, Division of Nephrology, Department of Medicine, 1959 NE Pacific
Street, Box 356521, HSB, BB1271, Seattle, WA 98195, USA.
(4)Duke University School of Nursing, DUMC Box 3322, 307 Trent Drive, Durham, NC 
27710, USA.
(5)Durham VA Geriatric Research, Education and Clinical Center, 508 Fulton
Street, Durham, NC 27705, USA; Duke University Medical Center, Division of
Geriatrics, Department of Medicine, Box DUMC 3003, Durham, NC 27710, USA.

This study examined whether chronic kidney disease (CKD) is associated with
recurrent falls in older adults in nursing homes (NHs). We used data abstracted
over a six month period from 510 NH residents with a history of falls.
Thirty-five percent of the NH residents had CKD. In adjusted analyses, the
incidence of recurrent falls was similar in those with and without CKD [fall rate
ratio (FRR) 1.00, 95% confidence interval (CI) 0.97-1.02]. Orthostatic
hypotension (FRR 1.52, 95% CI 1.12-2.05), history of falls during the prior six
month period (FRR 1.25, 95% CI 1.05-1.49), cane or walker use (FRR 1.64, 95% CI
1.16-2.33), and ambulatory dysfunction (FRR 1.47, 95% CI 1.23-1.75) were
independently associated with increased fall rate. CKD was not an important
predictor of falls in this cohort of nursing home residents with prior falls.
Instead, traditional fall risk factors were much more strongly associated with
recurrent falls.

Published by Elsevier Inc.

DOI: 10.1016/j.gerinurse.2014.12.012 
PMCID: PMC4393772
PMID: 25616732  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


27. Curr Opin Support Palliat Care. 2015 Mar;9(1):14-9. doi:
10.1097/SPC.0000000000000110.

Palliative and end-of-life care issues in chronic kidney disease.

Combs SA(1), Davison SN.

Author information: 
(1)aDepartment of Medicine, Harborview Medical Center, University of Washington, 
Seattle, Washington, USA bDivision of Nephrology and Immunology, Department of
Medicine, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada.

PURPOSE OF REVIEW: Patients with progressive chronic kidney disease (CKD) have
high morbidity, mortality, and symptom burden. Cardiovascular disease (CVD) and
congestive heart failure (CHF) often contribute to these burdens and should be
considered when providing recommendations for care. This review aims to summarize
recent literature relevant to the provision of palliative and end-of-life care
for patients with progressive CKD and specifically highlights issues relevant to 
those with CVD and CHF.
RECENT FINDINGS: Dialysis may not benefit older, frail patients with progressive 
CKD, especially those with other comorbidities. Patients managed conservatively
(i.e., without dialysis) may live as long as patients who elect to start
dialysis, with better preservation of function and quality of life and with fewer
acute care admissions. Decisions regarding dialysis initiation should be made on 
an individual basis, keeping in mind each patient's goals, comorbidities, and
underlying functional status. Conservative management of progressive kidney
disease is frequently not offered but is likely to benefit many older, frail
patients with comorbidities such as CHF and CVD.
SUMMARY: A palliative approach to the care of many patients with progressive CKD 
is essential to ensuring they receive appropriate quality care.

DOI: 10.1097/SPC.0000000000000110 
PMCID: PMC5497481
PMID: 25581447  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


28. Healthcare (Basel). 2015 Oct 30;3(4):1075-85. doi: 10.3390/healthcare3041075.

Ageing Renal Patients: We Need More Collaboration between Geriatric Services and 
Nephrology Departments.

Alston H(1), Burns A(2).

Author information: 
(1)Centre for Nephrology, Royal Free Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, Pond Street,
London NW3 2QG, UK. helen.alston@nhs.net.
(2)Centre for Nephrology, Royal Free Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, Pond Street,
London NW3 2QG, UK. aine.burns@nhs.net.

There has been a significant increase in the number of frail older patients
diagnosed with advanced chronic kidney disease (CKD) over the past thirty years. 
These elderly patients have high levels of comorbidity, and as a consequence the 
face of renal medicine is changing-There is an increasing need to focus on
traditionally geriatric areas of expertise such as falls prevention and
rehabilitation, and to shift our emphasis onto improving patient well-being
rather than longevity. Over the past decade, many nephrologists have found that
they are already acting as de facto "amateur geriatricians". This denies patients
both the benefits of specialist geriatric assessment, and equally importantly
denies them access to the wider geriatric multidisciplinary team. This article
describes the prevalence and underlying causes of the so-called "Geriatric
Giants" in patients with advanced CKD, and discusses possible improvements in
care that closer working with geriatricians could bring.

DOI: 10.3390/healthcare3041075 
PMCID: PMC4934632
PMID: 27417814 


29. J Vasc Surg. 2014 May;59(5):1323-30.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jvs.2013.11.076. Epub 2014
Jan 7.

Impact of amputation level and comorbidities on functional status of nursing home
residents after lower extremity amputation.

Vogel TR(1), Petroski GF(2), Kruse RL(3).

Author information: 
(1)Division of Vascular Surgery, University of Missouri, School of Medicine,
Columbia, Mo. Electronic address: vogeltr@health.missouri.edu.
(2)Department of Health Management and Informatics, University of Missouri,
School of Medicine, Columbia, Mo.
(3)Department of Family and Community Medicine, University of Missouri, School of
Medicine, Columbia, Mo.

OBJECTIVE: The ability of nursing home residents to function independently is
associated with their quality of life. The impact of amputations on functional
status in this population remains unclear. This analysis evaluated the effect of 
amputations-transmetatarsal (TM), below-knee (BK), and above-knee (AK)--on the
ability of residents to perform self-care activities.
METHODS: Medicare inpatient claims were linked with nursing home assessment data 
to identify admissions for amputation. The Minimum Data Set Activities of Daily
Living Long Form Score (0-28; higher numbers indicating greater impairment),
based on seven activities of daily living, was calculated before and after
amputation. Hierarchical modeling determined the effect of the surgery on
postamputation function of residents. Controlling for comorbidity, cognition, and
prehospital function allowed for evaluation of Activities of Daily Living
trajectories over time.
RESULTS: In total, 4965 residents underwent amputation: 490 TM, 1596 BK, and 2879
AK. Mean age was 81 years, and 54% of the patients were women. Most were white
(67%) or black (26.5%). Comorbidities before amputation included diabetes
mellitus (70.7%), coronary heart disease (57.1%), chronic kidney disease (53.6%),
and/or congestive heart failure (52.1%). Mortality within 30 days of hospital
discharge was 9.0%, and hospital readmission was 27.7%. Stroke, end-stage renal
disease, and poor baseline cognitive function were associated with the poorest
functional outcome after amputation. Compared with residents who received TM
amputation, those who had BK or AK amputation recovered more slowly and failed to
return to baseline function by 6 months. BK was found to have a superior
functional trajectory compared with AK.
CONCLUSIONS: Elderly nursing home residents undergoing BK or AK amputation failed
to return to their functional baseline within 6 months. Among frail elderly
nursing home residents, higher amputation level, stroke, end-stage renal disease,
poor baseline cognitive scores, and female sex were associated with inferior
functional status after amputation. These factors should be strongly assessed to 
maintain activities of daily living and quality of life in the nursing home
population.

Copyright © 2014 Society for Vascular Surgery. Published by Mosby, Inc. All
rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.jvs.2013.11.076 
PMCID: PMC4004653
PMID: 24406089  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


30. BMC Nephrol. 2013 Oct 22;14:228. doi: 10.1186/1471-2369-14-228.

Association of frailty and physical function in patients with non-dialysis CKD: a
systematic review.

Walker SR, Gill K, Macdonald K, Komenda P, Rigatto C, Sood MM, Bohm CJ, Storsley 
LJ, Tangri N(1).

Author information: 
(1)Seven Oaks Hospital, Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada. ntangri@sogh.mb.ca.

BACKGROUND: Frailty is a condition characterized by a decline in physical
function and functional capacity. Common symptoms of frailty, such as weakness
and exhaustion, are prevalent in patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD). The 
increased vulnerability of frail patients with coexisting CKD may place them at a
heightened risk of encountering additional health complications. The purpose of
this systematic review was to explore the link between frailty, CKD and clinical 
outcomes.
METHODS: We searched for cross sectional and prospective studies in the general
population and in the CKD population indexed in EMBASE, Pubmed, Web of Science,
CINAHL, Cochrane and Ageline examining the association between frailty and CKD
and those relating frailty in patients with CKD to clinical outcomes.
RESULTS: We screened 5,066 abstracts and retrieved 108 studies for full text
review. We identified 7 studies associating frailty or physical function to CKD. 
From the 7 studies, we identified only two studies that related frailty in
patients with CKD to a clinical outcome. CKD was consistently associated with
increasing frailty or reduced physical function [odds ratios (OR) 1.30 to 3.12]. 
In patients with CKD, frailty was associated with a greater than two-fold higher 
risk of dialysis and/or death [OR from 2.0 to 5.88].
CONCLUSIONS: CKD is associated with a higher risk of frailty or diminished
physical function. Furthermore, the presence of frailty in patients with CKD may 
lead to a higher risk of mortality. Further research must be conducted to
understand the mechanisms of frailty in CKD and to confirm its association with
clinical outcomes.

DOI: 10.1186/1471-2369-14-228 
PMCID: PMC4016413
PMID: 24148266  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


31. Am J Nephrol. 2013;38(4):307-15. doi: 10.1159/000355568. Epub 2013 Oct 4.

Physical performance and frailty in chronic kidney disease.

Reese PP(1), Cappola AR, Shults J, Townsend RR, Gadegbeku CA, Anderson C, Baker
JF, Carlow D, Sulik MJ, Lo JC, Go AS, Ky B, Mariani L, Feldman HI, Leonard MB;
CRIC Study Investigators.

Collaborators: Appel LJ, Feldman HI, Go AS, He J, Kusek JW, Lash JP, Ojo A,
Rahman M, Townsend RR.

Author information: 
(1)Renal Division, Department of Medicine, Perelman School of Medicine at the
University of Pennsylvania, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa., USA.

BACKGROUND: Poor physical performance and frailty are associated with elevated
risks of death and disability. Chronic kidney disease (CKD) is also strongly
associated with these outcomes. The risks of poor physical performance and
frailty among CKD patients, however, are not well established.
METHODS: We measured the Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB; a summary test
of gait speed, chair raises and balance; range 0-12) and the five elements of
frailty among 1,111 Chronic Renal Insufficiency Cohort participants. Adjusting
for demographics and multiple comorbidities, we fit a linear regression model for
the outcome of SPPB score and an ordinal logistic regression model for frailty
status.
RESULTS: Median (interquartile range, IQR) age was 65 (57-71) years, median
estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) for non-dialysis patients was 49
(36-62) ml/min/1.73 m(2), and median SPPB score was 9 (7-10). Seven percent of
participants were frail and 43% were pre-frail. Compared with the SPPB score for 
eGFR >60 ml/min/1.73 m(2), the SPPB was 0.51 points lower for eGFR 30-59; 0.61
points lower for eGFR 15-29, and 1.75 points lower for eGFR <15 (p < 0.01 for all
comparisons). eGFR 30-59 (odds ratio, OR 1.45; p = 0.024), eGFR 15-29 (OR 2.02; p
= 0.002) and eGFR <15 (OR 4.83; p < 0.001) were associated with worse frailty
status compared with eGFR >60 ml/min/1.73 m(2).
CONCLUSIONS: CKD severity was associated with poor physical performance and
frailty in a graded fashion. Future trials should determine if outcomes for CKD
patients with frailty and poor physical performance are improved by targeted
interventions.

© 2013 S. Karger AG, Basel.

DOI: 10.1159/000355568 
PMCID: PMC4019506
PMID: 24107579  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


32. Arch Gerontol Geriatr. 2013 Nov-Dec;57(3):328-32. doi:
10.1016/j.archger.2013.03.009. Epub 2013 Apr 6.

Chronic kidney disease (CKD) is an independent risk factor for long-term care
insurance (LTCI) need certification among older Japanese adults: a two-year
prospective cohort study.

Yamada M(1), Arai H, Nishiguchi S, Kajiwara Y, Yoshimura K, Sonoda T, Yukutake T,
Kayama H, Tanigawa T, Aoyama T.

Author information: 
(1)Department of Human Health Sciences, Kyoto University Graduate School of
Medicine, 53 Kawahara-cho, Shogoin, Sakyo-ku, Kyoto 606-8507, Japan.
yamada@hs.med.kyoto-u.ac.jp

CKD is associated with impairments in health status, physical function, and
frailty. The aim of the current prospective cohort study was to determine whether
CKD predicted new LTCI need certification among community-dwelling older Japanese
adults. This was a prospective cohort study. We analyzed the cohort data from a
prospective study, The Japan Multicenter Aging Cohort for Care Prevention
(J-MACC). We followed 8063 elderly adults for 2 years, and we analyzed the
relationship between CKD and LTCI need. The outcome studied was new certification
for LTCI service need during a 2-year period. We measured serum creatinine (the
estimated glomerular filtration rate; eGFR), serum albumin, frailty checklist
scores, and body mass index. During the 2-year follow-up, 536 subjects (6.6%)
were newly certified as needing LTCI services. We stratified the cohort according
to eGFR quartile and performed multivariate analyses using an eGFR value of
71.4-83.6 ml/min/1.73 m(2) as a reference. We found that subjects with eGFR
values <60.0 ml/min/1.73 m(2) had a significantly elevated risk of LTCI service
need (adjusted hazard ratio: 1.44 [95% CI 1.12-1.86]). Our results indicate that 
CKD is independently associated with new LTCI service need certification and is
an important marker of frailty in older adults.

Copyright © 2013 Elsevier Ireland Ltd. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.archger.2013.03.009 
PMID: 23566448  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


33. Geriatr Gerontol Int. 2013 Jul;13(3):519-27. doi: 10.1111/ggi.12017. Epub 2012
Dec 17.

Anemia in elderly patients: new insight into an old disorder.

Andrès E(1), Serraj K, Federici L, Vogel T, Kaltenbach G.

Author information: 
(1)Department of Internal Medicine, Diabetes and Metabolic Disorders, University 
Hospital of Strasbourg, Strasbourg, France. emmanuel.andres@chru-strasbourg.fr

Anemia is an important healthcare concern among the elderly. In these patients,
the anemia is often mild, with a hemoglobin level >10 g/dL. It is usually well
tolerated, but might be responsible for several proteiform and/or atypical
presenting complaints. In the elderly, anemia is usually of multifactorial
origin, including chronic inflammation, chronic kidney disease, nutrient
deficiencies and iron deficiency (approximately two-thirds of all cases). The
remaining cases are unexplained (unknown etiology). In the elderly, the classic
diagnosis of anemia, which is based on the mean corpuscular volume associated
with a low hemoglobin level, might not be accurate. A predefined standardized
diagnostic procedure should be followed. In the common case of frail elderly
patients, all investigations should be carefully considered and invasive
examinations undertaken where justified (risk-benefit balance). Nevertheless,
most cases of anemia require further investigation and the underlying cause
should be identified and treated whenever possible.

© 2012 Japan Geriatrics Society.

DOI: 10.1111/ggi.12017 
PMID: 23253055  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


34. Semin Dial. 2010 May-Jun;23(3):317-23. doi: 10.1111/j.1525-139X.2010.00736.x.

Thyroid hormone abnormalities and frailty in elderly patients with chronic kidney
disease: a hypothesis.

Abdel-Rahman EM(1), Mansour W, Holley JL.

Author information: 
(1)Division of Nephrology, Department of Internal Medicine, University of
Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA. ea6n@virginia.edu

Thyroid hormones play a crucial role in the metabolic activities of adults,
affecting almost every organ system. All types of thyroid diseases are
encountered in the elderly. As symptoms and signs of thyroid diseases may overlap
with what is considered to be "normal aging," the presence of a thyroid disorder 
may go undiagnosed in the elderly. This potential problem is further compounded
in elderly patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD), where the presence of an
underlying hormonal problem such as hypothyroidism may be erroneously attributed 
to multiple comorbidities, the aging process, or the kidney disease. Frailty is
being recognized as a contributing factor to the poor outcomes (hospitalization
and high mortality) in elderly patients with CKD. Predisposing factors leading to
frailty in elderly with CKD such as increased inflammatory markers, anemia, low
testosterone, sarcopenia, and depression are associated with thyroid hormonal
abnormalities. These associations are remarkable and raise the question of
whether routine monitoring and screening for thyroid hormone changes in elderly
CKD patients might be helpful in identifying reversible causes of frailty. In
this review, we will focus on the associations between thyroid hormone
abnormalities and the predisposing factors of frailty in elderly patients with
CKD. If a cause-effect relationship of thyroid hormone abnormalities and factors 
predisposing to frailty in CKD patients is established, identification and
treatment of thyroid abnormalities in this population would assume increased
importance.

DOI: 10.1111/j.1525-139X.2010.00736.x 
PMID: 20636925  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


35. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2010 Mar 16;55(11):1080-90. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2009.12.014.
Epub 2010 Jan 22.

Transcatheter aortic valve implantation for the treatment of severe symptomatic
aortic stenosis in patients at very high or prohibitive surgical risk: acute and 
late outcomes of the multicenter Canadian experience.

Rodés-Cabau J(1), Webb JG, Cheung A, Ye J, Dumont E, Feindel CM, Osten M,
Natarajan MK, Velianou JL, Martucci G, DeVarennes B, Chisholm R, Peterson MD,
Lichtenstein SV, Nietlispach F, Doyle D, DeLarochellière R, Teoh K, Chu V, Dancea
A, Lachapelle K, Cheema A, Latter D, Horlick E.

Author information: 
(1)Quebec Heart and Lung Institute, Laval University, Quebec City, Quebec,
Canada. josep.rodes@criucpq.ulaval.ca

Comment in
    Nat Rev Cardiol. 2010 Jul;7(7):359.
    J Am Coll Cardiol. 2010 Mar 16;55(11):1091-2.

OBJECTIVES: The aim of this study was: 1) to evaluate the acute and late outcomes
of a transcatheter aortic valve implantation (TAVI) program including both the
transfemoral (TF) and transapical (TA) approaches; and 2) to determine the
results of TAVI in patients deemed inoperable because of either porcelain aorta
or frailty.
BACKGROUND: Very few data exist on the results of a comprehensive TAVI program
including both TA and TF approaches for the treatment of severe aortic stenosis
in patients at very high or prohibitive surgical risk.
METHODS: Consecutive patients who underwent TAVI with the Edwards valve (Edwards 
Lifesciences, Inc., Irvine, California) between January 2005 and June 2009 in 6
Canadian centers were included.
RESULTS: A total of 345 procedures (TF: 168, TA: 177) were performed in 339
patients. The predicted surgical mortality (Society of Thoracic Surgeons risk
score) was 9.8 +/- 6.4%. The procedural success rate was 93.3%, and 30-day
mortality was 10.4% (TF: 9.5%, TA: 11.3%). After a median follow-up of 8 months
(25th to 75th interquartile range: 3 to 14 months) the mortality rate was 22.1%. 
The predictors of cumulative late mortality were peri-procedural sepsis (hazard
ratio [HR]: 3.49, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 1.48 to 8.28) or need for
hemodynamic support (HR: 2.58, 95% CI: 1.11 to 6), pulmonary hypertension (PH)
(HR: 1.88, 95% CI: 1.17 to 3), chronic kidney disease (CKD) (HR: 2.30, 95% CI:
1.38 to 3.84), and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) (HR: 1.75, 95%
CI: 1.09 to 2.83). Patients with either porcelain aorta (18%) or frailty (25%)
exhibited acute outcomes similar to the rest of the study population, and
porcelain aorta patients tended to have a better survival rate at 1-year
follow-up.
CONCLUSIONS: A TAVI program including both TF and TA approaches was associated
with comparable mortality as predicted by surgical risk calculators for the
treatment of patients at very high or prohibitive surgical risk, including
porcelain aorta and frail patients. Baseline (PH, COPD, CKD) and peri-procedural 
(hemodynamic support, sepsis) factors but not the approach determined worse
outcomes.

Copyright 2010 American College of Cardiology Foundation. Published by Elsevier
Inc. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.jacc.2009.12.014 
PMID: 20096533  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


36. Adv Chronic Kidney Dis. 2009 Nov;16(6):420-9. doi: 10.1053/j.ackd.2009.07.008.

The intersection of geriatrics and chronic kidney disease: frailty and disability
among older adults with kidney disease.

Cook WL(1).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Medicine, Division of Geriatrics, University of British Columbia
and St. Paul's Hospital, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada.
wcook@providencehealth.bc.ca

Older adults (aged >or=65 years) comprise the largest segment of the CKD
population, and impaired kidney function is linked with unsuccessful aging.
Individuals across the spectrum of kidney disease have clinical features of the
frailty phenotype, suggesting that frailty is not confined to old age among
vulnerable populations. This manifests as a high prevalence of impaired physical 
performance, emergent geriatric syndromes, disability, and risk of death.
Considering the multiple system involvement underlying the symptoms and deficits 
seen in CKD, especially in the more severe stages, the concept of frailty is a
highly useful tool to identify older adults with kidney disease who are on the
trajectory of vulnerability leading to decline and death. Further work is needed 
to characterize the relationship between kidney disease and frailty and to
identify opportunities to intervene.

DOI: 10.1053/j.ackd.2009.07.008 
PMID: 19801132  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


37. Artif Organs. 2009 Jul;33(7):570-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1525-1594.2009.00740.x.

Chronic kidney disease, transplantation practices and transplantation law in
Pakistan: opportunity for a global meditation.

Akhtar F(1).

Author information: 
(1)Health Department Punjab, Lahore, Pakistan. akhtar.bajwa@gmail.com

The majority of countries have enacted edicts to regulate organ transplantation
due to mounting recognition of its intricacies and increasing level of global
disquiet. Frail national economy and status of health care infrastructure
restricts access of the local population to both dialysis and transplantation in 
Pakistan. There is a surge in kidney transplantation activities, however. I have 
reported the enormity of organ crime in Pakistan. The number of commercial renal 
transplants range from 3000 to 4500. Foreign nationals share the marketplace.
There are current attempts from the government to stop organ trade by strictly
enforcing a recently sanctioned law on organ transplantation. Scarcity of
comprehensive reliable data has hampered plausible assessments and indispensable 
modifications to facilitate designs for the future health care. Alternatives to
organ transplantation will augment the choice of treatment modalities for a
proliferating end-stage renal disease (ESRD) population. The whole array of
existing therapeutic modalities for ESRD has to be utilized. Promoting a fresh
culture of organ donation by strengthening of the family institution may be
another objective.

DOI: 10.1111/j.1525-1594.2009.00740.x 
PMID: 19566737  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


38. Am J Med. 2009 Jul;122(7):664-71.e2. doi: 10.1016/j.amjmed.2009.01.026.

Frailty and chronic kidney disease: the Third National Health and Nutrition
Evaluation Survey.

Wilhelm-Leen ER(1), Hall YN, K Tamura M, Chertow GM.

Author information: 
(1)Stanford University School of Medicine, Palo Alto, CA 94304, USA.
ewilhelm@stanford.edu

BACKGROUND: Frailty is common in the elderly and in persons with chronic
diseases. Few studies have examined the association of frailty with chronic
kidney disease.
METHODS: We used data from the Third National Health and Nutrition Examination
Survey to estimate the prevalence of frailty among persons with chronic kidney
disease. We created a definition of frailty based on established validated
criteria, modified to accommodate available data. We used logistic regression to 
determine whether and to what degree stages of chronic kidney disease were
associated with frailty. We also examined factors that might mediate the
association between frailty and chronic kidney disease.
RESULTS: The overall prevalence of frailty was 2.8%. However, among persons with 
moderate to severe chronic kidney disease (estimated glomerular filtration rate <
45 mL/min/1.73 m2), 20.9% were frail. The odds of frailty were significantly
increased among all stages of chronic kidney disease, even after adjustment for
the residual effects of age, sex, race, and prevalent chronic diseases. The odds 
of frailty associated with chronic kidney disease were only marginally attenuated
with additional adjustment for sarcopenia, anemia, acidosis, inflammation,
vitamin D deficiency, hypertension, and cardiovascular disease. Frailty and
chronic kidney disease were independently associated with mortality.
CONCLUSION: Frailty is significantly associated with all stages of chronic kidney
disease and particularly with moderate to severe chronic kidney disease.
Potential mechanisms underlying the chronic kidney disease and frailty connection
remain elusive.

DOI: 10.1016/j.amjmed.2009.01.026 
PMCID: PMC4117255
PMID: 19559169  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


39. Adv Chronic Kidney Dis. 2007 Jul;14(3):279-83.

Assisted peritoneal dialysis.

Povlsen JV(1), Ivarsen P.

Author information: 
(1)Department of Renal Medicine C, Aarhus University Hospital, Skejby, Aarhus,
Denmark. jvpovlsen@stofanet.dk <jvpovlsen@stofanet.dk>

Elderly patients are the largest and fastest growing group of patients with
chronic kidney disease maintained on dialysis in the world. Because of advanced
age and a heavy burden of comorbidities, the elderly are usually not candidates
for kidney transplantation and are less likely to be offered peritoneal dialysis 
(PD). There is, however, growing evidence that the use of community nurses to
assist with PD and the introduction of programs for assisted peritoneal dialysis 
(aPD) targeting these frail, elderly patients may enable more elderly patients to
have their PD treatment at home. Suitable candidates for aPD are incident
end-stage kidney disease patients preferring PD but unable to perform their own
treatment because of comorbidities, physical disabilities, or psychosocial
problems; prevalent, previous autonomous PD patients who have lost their
independence because of advanced age or an increased burden of comorbidities; or 
prevalent hemodialysis (HD) patients switched from HD to aPD because of their own
preference, failure of vascular access for HD, or an inability to tolerate HD. We
believe that aPD in the future will prove to be a safe and feasible complementary
alternative to in-center HD for the growing group of frail, elderly patients with
end-stage kidney disease.

DOI: 10.1053/j.ackd.2007.03.008 
PMID: 17603982  [Indexed for MEDLINE]
