//(frail AND (frail OR phenotype OR index)) AND (renal OR kidney) AND complication
//
1. Langenbecks Arch Surg. 2018 Dec;403(8):999-1005. doi: 10.1007/s00423-018-1726-6. 
Epub 2018 Nov 10.

Safety and efficacy of subtotal or total parathyroidectomy for patients with
secondary or tertiary hyperparathyroidism in four academic centers in the
Netherlands.

van der Plas WY(1), Dulfer RR(2), Koh EY(3), Vogt L(4), Appelman-Dijkstra NM(5), 
Schepers A(6), Rotmans JI(7), Pol RA(1), van Ginhoven TM(2), Hoorn EJ(8), Nieveen
van Dijkum EJM(3), Engelsman AF(3), de Borst MH(9), Kruijff S(10); Dutch
Hyperparathyroidism Study Group (DHSG).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Surgery, University Medical Center Groningen, University of
Groningen, Hanzeplein 1, 9700 RB, Groningen, The Netherlands.
(2)Department of Surgery, Erasmus Medical Center, Erasmus University Rotteredam, 
Rotterdam, The Netherlands.
(3)Department of Surgery, Amsterdam UMC, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The 
Netherlands.
(4)Department of Nephrology, Amsterdam UMC, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam,
The Netherlands.
(5)Department of Endocrinology, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden
University, Leiden, The Netherlands.
(6)Department of Surgery, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden University,
Leiden, The Netherlands.
(7)Department of Internal Medicine, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden
University, Leiden, The Netherlands.
(8)Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Nephrology and Transplantation,
Erasmus Medical Center, Rotterdam, The Netherlands.
(9)Department of Nephrology, University Medical Center Groningen, University of
Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands.
(10)Department of Surgery, University Medical Center Groningen, University of
Groningen, Hanzeplein 1, 9700 RB, Groningen, The Netherlands. s.kruijff@umcg.nl.

PURPOSE: Hyperparathyroidism (HPT) is a common abnormality in patients with
end-stage renal disease (ESRD). Since the introduction of cinacalcet in 2004, a
shift from surgery toward predominantly medical treatment has occurred. Surgery
is thought to be associated with more complications than oral medication. The aim
of this retrospective study was to evaluate 30-day outcomes and effectiveness of 
parathyroidectomy (PTx) in ESRD patients in the Netherlands.
METHODS: A national database containing data from four academic medical centers
in the Netherlands of patients with ESRD-related HPT, who had undergone PTx and
kidney transplantation between 1994 and 2015, was established. Primary endpoints 
were 30-day mortality and complication rate. Secondary endpoints were biochemical
measurements.
RESULTS: We identified 187 HPT patients undergoing PTx, with a median age of
46 years. Median preoperative PTH level was 866 pg/mL (interquartile range [IQR] 
407-1547 pg/mL). At 3 months, the median PTH drop from baseline was 93% (IQR,
71-98%) to a median of 61 pg/mL (IQR, 23-148 pg/mL, p < 0.001). Over the 25-year 
inclusion period, 13 patients (7.0%) required re-exploration for persistent or
recurrent disease. Thirty-day mortality and complication rate were 0.0% and 7.9% 
respectively. Median serum calcium levels improved significantly postoperatively 
from 2.6 (2.4-2.8) mmol/L to 2.3 (2.1-2.5) mmol/L (p < 0.001).
CONCLUSIONS: PTx is a safe and effective procedure in the frail ESRD population. 
These data show that there should be no reluctance for surgical intervention and 
when indicated, nephrologists can safely refer these patients for PTx.

DOI: 10.1007/s00423-018-1726-6 
PMCID: PMC6328516
PMID: 30415287 


2. Transpl Int. 2019 Jan;32(1):66-74. doi: 10.1111/tri.13330. Epub 2018 Aug 28.

Frailty has a significant influence on postoperative complications after kidney
transplantation-a prospective study on short-term outcomes.

Schopmeyer L(1), El Moumni M(1), Nieuwenhuijs-Moeke GJ(2), Berger SP(3), Bakker
SJL(3), Pol RA(1).

Author information: 
(1)Division of Transplantation Surgery, Department of Surgery, University Medical
Center Groningen, University of Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands.
(2)Department of Anesthesiology, University Medical Center Groningen, University 
of Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands.
(3)Department of Nephrology, University Medical Center Groningen, University of
Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands.

Currently, there are no tools to predict postsurgery outcome after kidney
transplantation. This study assesses whether frailty influence 30-day
postoperative complications after kidney transplantation. One-hundred and fifty
kidney transplantations were prospectively included. Frailty was assessed using a
frailty indicator, consisting of 15 questions, covering most domains of
functioning. Postoperative complications were measured by the Comprehensive
Complication Index (CCI). Using a linear regression model, 30-day postoperative
complications and frailty correlation were adjusted for confounders, including
sex, age, ASA Score, Charlson Comorbidity Index, hypertension, BMI, smoking,
dialysis, duration of dialysis, type of transplantation, and retransplantation.
The mean frailty score was 2.07(±1.6) and 23 patients were classified as frail
(GFI ≥4). The mean CCI-score was 18(±15.6), the mean CCI-score for "frail"
patients 30.1(±17.2) compared to 15.5 (±14.2) for "non-frail" patients (N = 116).
In a regression analysis, a significant relationship between CCI-score and
frailty (β = 13.3; 95% CI 5.7-20.9; P = 0.0007) and transplantation type (β =
4.9; 95% CI: 0.72-9.16; P = 0.02) was found, independent of confounders. In
conclusion, frailty and type of transplantation are independent factors
associated with an increased risk of postoperative complications.

© 2018 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd
on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT.

DOI: 10.1111/tri.13330 
PMID: 30099780  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


3. Surg J (N Y). 2018 May 23;4(2):e66-e77. doi: 10.1055/s-0038-1655756. eCollection 
2018 Apr.

The Impact of Frailty on Postoperative Cardiopulmonary Complications in the
Emergency General Surgery Population.

Akyar S(1), Armenia SJ(1), Ratnani P(1), Merchant AM(1).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Surgery, New Jersey Medical School, Rutgers Biomedical and
Health Sciences, Rutgers University, Newark, New Jersey.

Background  The burden of frail patients undergoing emergency general surgery
(EGS) is increasing rapidly and this population is particularly susceptible to
postoperative cardiopulmonary complications and mortality. We aimed to determine 
the association between frailty, as defined by the previously described modified 
frailty index (mFI), and postoperative respiratory complications (unplanned
reintubation, pneumonia, and prolonged ventilation), cardiac complications
(myocardial infarction and cardiac arrest), and mortality. We also sought to
identify the most significant determinants of frailty in the highest risk
patients based on the specific variables comprising the mFI. Methods  We
performed a retrospective observational analysis of the prospectively collected
American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program
database. Files from 2005 to 2015 identified 132,765 inpatients who underwent
EGS. mFI scores were calculated for each patient. The effect of increasing
frailty on unplanned reintubation, pneumonia, prolonged ventilation, myocardial
infarction, cardiac arrest, and mortality was evaluated using bivariate analysis.
Multivariable logistic regression was used to compare mFI with additional
predictor variables including race, gender, physical status as defined by the
American Society of Anesthesiologists, disseminated cancer, renal failure,
smoking status, sepsis, wound presence/classification, dyspnea, and previous
ventilator dependence. Results  Unplanned reintubation, pneumonia, prolonged
ventilation, myocardial infarction, cardiac arrest, and mortality were
significantly associated with frailty, and the odds of each postoperative
complication increased with increasing mFI score. Of the frailest patients (mFI
≥3) that experienced cardiopulmonary complications or mortality, the variables of
the mFI that contributed most to frailty were hypertension requiring medication
and functional status before surgery. Conclusions  A higher mFI score is
associated with increased odds of postoperative cardiopulmonary complications and
mortality in the EGS population. Specific variables of the mFI can also provide
valuable information for assessing odds in the frailest patients undergoing EGS.

DOI: 10.1055/s-0038-1655756 
PMCID: PMC5966303
PMID: 29796424 


4. Expert Rev Anticancer Ther. 2018 Mar;18(3):237-250. doi:
10.1080/14737140.2018.1431530. Epub 2018 Jan 25.

Indications, complications, and outcomes following surgical management of locally
advanced and metastatic renal cell carcinoma.

González J(1), Gaynor JJ(2), Alameddine M(2), Esteban M(3), Ciancio G(2).

Author information: 
(1)a Servicio de Urología , Hospital Central de la Cruz Roja San José y Santa
Adela , Madrid , Spain.
(2)b Department of Surgery (Division of Transplantation), Department of Urology
and the Miami Transplant Institute , University of Miami Miller School of
Medicine, Jackson Memorial Hospital , Miami , FL , USA.
(3)c Servicio de Urología , Hospital Nacional de Parapléjicos , Toledo , Spain.

INTRODUCTION: Surgery may set the basis for a potential cure or would provide the
best achievable quality of life in locally advanced or metastatic renal cell
carcinoma (mRCC). However, survival extension with this approach would be scarce 
and not exempt from adverse events, thus preventing its recommendation in an
already frail patient. An evidence based analysis on the role of surgery in each 
of the possible clinical scenarios involved under this heading may provide a
clear picture on this issue and would be of value in the decision making process.
Areas covered: Current literature was queried in PubMed/Medline in a systematic
fashion. Manuscripts included were selected according to the quality of the data 
provided. A narrative review strategy was adopted to summarize the evidence
acquired. Expert commentary: A surgery-based multimodal treatment approach should
be strongly considered after adequate counseling in locally advanced and mRCC,
since it may provide for additional benefits in terms of survival. However, a
critical reevaluation of its adequacy, optimal timing, and selection of ideal
candidates is currently ongoing.

DOI: 10.1080/14737140.2018.1431530 
PMID: 29353520  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


5. J Frailty Aging. 2017;6(2):103-106. doi: 10.14283/jfa.2017.14.

Frailty in End-Stage Renal Disease Patients under Dialysis and Its Association
with Clinical and Biochemical Markers.

Poveda V(1), Filgueiras M, Miranda V, Santos-Silva A, Paúl C, Costa E.

Author information: 
(1)Elísio Costa, Laboratório de Bioquímica, Departamento de Ciências Biológicas, 
Universidade do Porto, Rua de Jorge Viterbo Ferreira, 228, 4050-313 Porto,
Portugal, Email: emcosta@ff.up.pt.

Frailty is a common complication in elderly patients with end-stage renal disease
(ESRD) under dialysis, which is a strong risk factor for low quality of life,
morbidity, and mortality. In this work, we aimed to evaluate the prevalence of
frailty in a group of Portuguese ESRD patients, and its association with
socio-demographic, clinical and biochemical markers. We performed a
cross-sectional study with 83 ESRD patients (44 males and 39 females, 64.3
[±14.6] years old) on regular dialysis. The classification of the ESRD patients
as robust, pre-frail and frail was performed using the FRAIL questionnaire.
Social support, data about sociodemographic and comorbidities, and
haematological, iron status, dialysis adequacy, nutritional and inflammatory
markers were also evaluated. Our results confirmed that frailty is a highly
prevalent condition in ESRD patients, particularly in female patients. An
association between FRAIL score and increased depressive symptoms, presence of
hypertension and decrease nutritional status was also found.

DOI: 10.14283/jfa.2017.14 
PMID: 28555712  [Indexed for MEDLINE]

Conflict of interest statement: none


6. J Vasc Surg. 2017 Feb;65(2):459-470. doi: 10.1016/j.jvs.2016.07.119. Epub 2016
Nov 7.

Risk stratification for the development of respiratory adverse events following
vascular surgery using the Society of Vascular Surgery's Vascular Quality
Initiative.

Genovese EA(1), Fish L(2), Chaer RA(2), Makaroun MS(2), Baril DT(3).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Surgery, Division of Vascular Surgery, University of Pittsburgh 
Medical Center, Pittsburgh, Pa. Electronic address: genovesee@upmc.edu.
(2)Department of Surgery, Division of Vascular Surgery, University of Pittsburgh 
Medical Center, Pittsburgh, Pa.
(3)Department of Surgery, Division of Vascular and Endovascular Surgery,
University of California Los Angeles Health, Los Angeles, Calif.

OBJECTIVE: Postoperative respiratory adverse events (RAEs) are associated with
high rates of morbidity and mortality in general surgery, however, little is
known about these complications in the vascular surgery population, a frail
subset with multiple comorbidities. The objective of this study was to describe
the contemporary incidence of RAEs in vascular surgery patients, the risk factors
for this complication, and the overall impact of RAEs on patient outcomes.
METHODS: The Vascular Quality Initiative was queried (2003-2014) for patients who
underwent endovascular abdominal aortic repair, open abdominal aortic aneurysm
repair, thoracic endovascular aortic repair, suprainguinal bypass, or
infrainguinal bypass. A mixed-effects logistic regression model determined the
independent risk factors for RAEs. Using a random 85% of the cohort, a risk
prediction score for RAEs was created, and the score was validated using the
remaining 15% of the cohort, comparing the predicted to the actual incidence of
RAE and determining the area under the receiver operating characteristic curve.
The independent risk of in-hospital mortality and discharge to a nursing facility
associated with RAEs was determined using a mixed-effects logistic regression to 
control for baseline patient characteristics, operative variables, and other
postoperative adverse events.
RESULTS: The cohort consisted of 52,562 patients, with a 5.4% incidence of RAEs. 
The highest rates of RAEs were seen in current smokers (6.1%), recent acute
myocardial infarction (10.1%), symptomatic congestive heart failure (9.9%),
chronic obstructive pulmonary disease requiring oxygen therapy (11.0%), urgent
and emergent procedures (6.4% and 25.9%, respectively), open abdominal aortic
aneurysm repairs (17.6%), in situ suprainguinal bypasses (9.68%), and thoracic
endovascular aortic repairs (9.6%). The variables included in the risk prediction
score were age, body mass index, smoking status, congestive heart failure
severity, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease severity, degree of renal
insufficiency, ambulatory status, transfer status, urgency, and operative type.
The predicted compared with the actual RAE incidence were highly correlated, with
a correlation coefficient of 0.943 (P < .0001) and a c-statistic = 0.818. RAEs
had a significantly higher rates of in-hospital mortality (25.4% vs 1.2%; P <
.0001; adjusted odds ratio, 5.85; P < .0001), and discharge to a nursing facility
(57.8% vs 19.0%; P < .0001; adjusted odds ratio, 3.14; P < .0001).
CONCLUSIONS: RAEs are frequent and one of the strongest risk factors for
in-hospital mortality and inability to be discharged home. Our risk prediction
score accurately stratifies patients based on key demographics, comorbidities,
presentation, and operative type that can be used to guide patient counseling,
preoperative optimization, and postoperative management. Furthermore, it may be
useful in developing quality benchmarks for RAE following major vascular surgery.

Copyright © 2016 Society for Vascular Surgery. Published by Elsevier Inc. All
rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.jvs.2016.07.119 
PMCID: PMC5408577
PMID: 27832989  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


7. J Trauma Acute Care Surg. 2016 Dec;81(6):1150-1155.

The impact of frailty on failure-to-rescue in geriatric trauma patients: A
prospective study.

Joseph B(1), Phelan H, Hassan A, Orouji Jokar T, O'Keeffe T, Azim A, Gries L,
Kulvatunyou N, Latifi R, Rhee P.

Author information: 
(1)From the Department of Surgery (B.J., A.H., T.O.J., T.O.K., A.A., L.G., N.K., 
R.L., P.R.), Division of Trauma, Critical Care, Burns and Emergency Surgery,
University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona; and Department of Surgery, Division of
Trauma, Critical Care, Burns, and Acute Care Surgery (H.P.), University of Texas 
Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, Texas.

INTRODUCTION: Failure-to-rescue (FTR) (defined as death from a major
complication) is considered as an index of hospital quality in trauma patients.
However, the role of frailty in FTR events remains unclear. We hypothesized that 
FTR rate is higher in elderly frail trauma patients.
METHODS: We performed a prospective cohort study of all elderly (age ≥ 65 years) 
trauma patients presenting at our level one trauma center. Patient's frailty
status was calculated utilizing the Trauma Specific Frailty Index (TSFI) within
24 hours of admission. Patients were stratified into non-frail, pre-frail, and
frail. FTR was defined as death from a major complication (respiratory,
infectious, cardiac, and renal). Binary logistic regression analysis was
performed after adjusting for age, gender, injury severity (ISS), and vital
parameters to assess the relationship between frailty status and FTR.
RESULTS: A total of 368 elderly trauma patients were evaluated of which 25% (n = 
93) were non-frail, 38% (n = 139) pre-frail, and 37% (n = 136) frail. Overall,
30% of the patients developed in-hospital complications; of them, mortality
occurred in 26% of the patients (FTR group). In the FTR group, 69% of the
patients were frail compared to 17% pre-frail and 14% non-frail (p = 0.002). On
multivariate regression analysis for predictors of FTR, frail status was an
independent predictor of FTR (OR [95% CI] = 2.67 [1.37-5.20]; p = 0.004). On
sensitivity analysis, positive predictive value of TSFI for FTR was 69% and
negative predictive value for FTR was 67%.
CONCLUSION: In elderly trauma patients, the presence of frailty increased the
odds of FTR almost threefold as compared to non-frail. Although FTR has been
considered as an indicator of health care quality, the findings of this study
suggest that frailty status independently contributes to FTR. This needs to be
considered in the future development of quality metrics, particularly in the case
of geriatric trauma patients.
LEVEL OF EVIDENCE: Prognostic study, level II.

DOI: 10.1097/TA.0000000000001250 
PMID: 27602908  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


8. World Neurosurg. 2016 Nov;95:548-555.e4. doi: 10.1016/j.wneu.2016.08.029. Epub
2016 Aug 18.

Development of a Metastatic Spinal Tumor Frailty Index (MSTFI) Using a Nationwide
Database and Its Association with Inpatient Morbidity, Mortality, and Length of
Stay After Spine Surgery.

De la Garza Ramos R(1), Goodwin CR(1), Jain A(2), Abu-Bonsrah N(1), Fisher CG(3),
Bettegowda C(1), Sciubba DM(4).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Neurosurgery, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine,
Baltimore, Maryland, USA.
(2)Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Johns Hopkins University School of
Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland, USA.
(3)Divison of Spine, Department of Orthopaedics, University of British Columbia, 
Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada.
(4)Department of Neurosurgery, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine,
Baltimore, Maryland, USA. Electronic address: dsciubb1@jhmi.edu.

OBJECTIVE: The aim of this study was to develop a perioperative metastatic spinal
tumor frailty index (MSTFI) that could predict morbidity, mortality, and length
of stay.
METHODS: A large inpatient hospitalization database was searched from 2002 to
2011 to identify 4583 patients with spinal metastasis from breast (21.1%), lung
(34.1%), thyroid (3.8%), renal (19.9%), and prostate (21.1%) cancer who underwent
surgery. A multiple logistic regression model identified 9 independent parameters
that were used to construct the MSTFI: anemia, chronic lung disease,
coagulopathy, electrolyte abnormalities, pulmonary circulation disorders, renal
failure, malnutrition, emergent/urgent admission, and anterior/combined surgical 
approach. Patients with 0 points were categorized as "not frail," 1 as "mildly
frail," 2 as "moderately frail," and ≥3 as "severely frail."
RESULTS: The overall perioperative complication rate was 19.3% and in-patient
mortality was 3.0%. Compared with patients with no frailty, patients with
moderate frailty (odds ratio [OR] 5.15; 95% confidence interval [95% CI]
2.44-10.86), and severe frailty (OR 5.74; 95% CI 2.69-12.24) had significantly
increased odds of inpatient mortality (all P < 0.001). Similarly, patients with
mild frailty (OR 1.88; 95% CI 1.33-2.66), moderate frailty (OR 3.83; 95% CI
2.71-5.41), and severe frailty (OR 6.97; 95% CI 4.98-9.74) had significantly
increased odds of developing a major in-hospital complication (all P < 0.001).
Length of stay also increased significantly by MSTFI (P < 0.001).
CONCLUSIONS: In surgically treated patients with spinal metastasis, certain
perioperative parameters may significantly predict the risk of major in-hospital 
complications and mortality.

Copyright © 2016. Published by Elsevier Inc.

DOI: 10.1016/j.wneu.2016.08.029 
PMID: 27544340  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


9. Ann Vasc Surg. 2016 Aug;35:19-29. doi: 10.1016/j.avsg.2016.01.052. Epub 2016 Jun 
2.

Preoperative Frailty Increases Risk of Nonhome Discharge after Elective Vascular 
Surgery in Home-Dwelling Patients.

Arya S(1), Long CA(2), Brahmbhatt R(2), Shafii S(2), Brewster LP(3), Veeraswamy
R(2), Johnson TM 2nd(4), Johanning JM(5).

Author information: 
(1)Division of Vascular Surgery, Department of Surgery, Emory University School
of Medicine, Atlanta, GA; Surgical Service Line, Atlanta VA Medical Center,
Decatur, GA. Electronic address: shipra.arya@emory.edu.
(2)Division of Vascular Surgery, Department of Surgery, Emory University School
of Medicine, Atlanta, GA.
(3)Division of Vascular Surgery, Department of Surgery, Emory University School
of Medicine, Atlanta, GA; Surgical Service Line, Atlanta VA Medical Center,
Decatur, GA.
(4)Division of General Medicine and Geriatrics, Department of Medicine, Emory
University School of Medicine.
(5)Division of Vascular Surgery, Department of Surgery, University of Nebraska
Medical Center, Omaha, NE.

BACKGROUND: Patient-centered quality outcomes such as disposition after surgery
are increasingly being scrutinized. Preoperative factors predictive of nonhome
discharge (DC) may identify at-risk patients for targeted interventions. This
study examines the association among preoperative risk factors, frailty, and
nonhome DC after elective vascular surgery procedures in patients living at home.
METHODS: The 2011-2012 National Surgical Quality Improvement Project database was
queried to identify all home-dwelling patients who underwent elective vascular
procedures (endovascular and open aortic aneurysm repair, suprainguinal and
infrainguinal bypasses, peripheral endovascular interventions, carotid
endarterectomy, and stent). Preoperative frailty was measured using the modified 
frailty index (mFI; derived from Canadian Study of Health and Aging). Univariate 
and multivariate logistic regression analysis was performed to examine the
association of frailty and nonhome DC.
RESULTS: Of 15,843 home-dwelling patients, 1,177 patients (7.4%) did not return
home postoperatively. Frailty (mFI > 0.25) conferred a significantly increased
2-fold risk of nonhome DC disposition for each procedure type. Frailty, female
gender, open procedures, increasing age, end-stage renal disease, and occurrence 
of any postoperative complication were associated with increased risk of nonhome 
DC. On multivariate logistic regression analysis, frailty increased the odds of
nonhome DC by 60% (odds ratio 1.6, 95% confidence interval 1.4-1.8) after
adjusting for other covariates. In the presence of complications, the risk of
nonhome DC was 27.5% in frail versus 16.5% in nonfrail patients (P < 0.001). In
the absence of complications, although absolute risk was lower, frail patients
were nearly twice as likely to not return home (frail 5.5% vs. nonfrail 2.75%,
P < 0.001).
CONCLUSIONS: Frail home-dwelling patients undergoing elective vascular procedures
are at high risk of not returning home after surgery. Preoperative frailty
assessment appears to hold potential for counseling regarding postsurgery
disposition and DC planning.

Published by Elsevier Inc.

DOI: 10.1016/j.avsg.2016.01.052 
PMID: 27263810  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


10. World J Urol. 2017 Jan;35(1):21-26. doi: 10.1007/s00345-016-1845-z. Epub 2016 May
12.

Preoperative frailty predicts postoperative complications and mortality in
urology patients.

Isharwal S(1), Johanning JM(2)(3), Dwyer JG(4), Schimid KK(5), LaGrange CA(4).

Author information: 
(1)Division of Urology, University of Nebraska Medical Center, 984110 Nebraska
Medical Center, Omaha, NE, 68198-4110, USA. isharwal.sudhir@gmail.com.
(2)Division of Vascular Surgery, University of Nebraska Medical Center, Omaha,
NE, USA.
(3)Department of Surgery, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Omaha, NE, USA.
(4)Division of Urology, University of Nebraska Medical Center, 984110 Nebraska
Medical Center, Omaha, NE, 68198-4110, USA.
(5)Department of Biostatistics, University of Nebraska Medical Center, Omaha, NE,
USA.

PURPOSE: Our objective was to determine the impact of preoperative frailty, as
measured by validated Risk Analysis Index (RAI), on the occurrence of
postoperative complications after urologic surgeries in a national database
comprised of diverse practice groups and cases.
STUDY DESIGN: The National Surgical Quality Improvement Program (NSQIP) database 
was queried from 2005 to 2011 for a list of abdominal, vaginal, transurethral and
scrotal urological surgeries using Current Procedural Terminology codes. The
study population was subdivided into two groups based on the nature of procedures
performed: complex procedures (inpatient) and simple procedures (outpatient).
Risk Analysis Index score was calculated using preoperative NSQIP variables to
determine preoperative frailty. Major postoperative morbidities (pulmonary,
cardiovascular, renal and infectious), mortality, return to operating room,
discharge destination and readmission to the hospital were examined.
RESULTS: The study identified 42,715 patients who underwent urological
procedures, 25,693 complex and 17,022 simple procedures. Mean RAI score (range)
was 7.75 (0-53). The majority of patients scored low on the RAI (90.57 % with
RAI < 10). As the RAI score increased, there was a significant increase in
postoperative complication and mortality rate (both p < 0.0001). Similarly, the
rate of return to operating room and hospital readmission rate increased as RAI
increased (both p < 0.0001). Additionally, rate of discharge to home decreased.
Interestingly, mortality rate in patients with high RAI did not differ comparing 
simple to complex procedures (p = 0.90), whereas complications were significantly
greater in the complex operation (p = 0.01).
CONCLUSIONS: Increase in frailty, as measured by RAI score, is associated with
increased postoperative complications and mortality. RAI may allow for rapid
identification and counseling of patients who are at high risk of adverse
perioperative outcomes.

DOI: 10.1007/s00345-016-1845-z 
PMID: 27172940  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


11. JAMA Surg. 2015 Jan;150(1):30-6. doi: 10.1001/jamasurg.2014.863.

The significance of preoperative impaired sensorium on surgical outcomes in
nonemergent general surgical operations.

Gajdos C(1), Kile D(2), Hawn MT(3), Finlayson E(4), Henderson WG(2), Robinson
TN(1).

Author information: 
(1)Division of GI, Tumor and Endocrine Surgery, Department of Surgery, University
of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora.
(2)Colorado Health Outcomes Program, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical
Campus, Aurora.
(3)Section of Gastrointestinal Surgery, Division of General Surgery, Department
of Surgery, University of Alabama at Birmingham.
(4)Division of General Surgery, Department of Surgery, University of California
at San Francisco.

IMPORTANCE: With an aging population, preoperative assessment of the frail older 
adult requires evaluation beyond simply accounting for chronic diseases. Impaired
cognition is a recognized characteristic of the frail older adult.
OBJECTIVE: To examine the effect of preoperative impaired sensorium (IS) on
general surgical outcomes.
DESIGN, SETTING, AND PARTICIPANTS: Retrospective cohort study using data between 
January 2005 and December 2010 at academic and community hospitals participating 
in the American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement
Program. Patients undergoing nonemergent general surgical operations were
studied. Multivariable logistic regression involving 45 preoperative
patient-level risk factors and comorbidities was used to calculate the
conditional probability of having IS. Patients having and not having preoperative
IS were matched on their propensity scores using a 1:1 greedy matching technique.
Propensity score matching resulted in almost all (n = 1765) patients with IS
uniquely matching to a patient without IS, resulting in a cohort size of 3530.
Complication rates between patients with and without IS were compared.
MAIN OUTCOMES AND MEASURES: Rates of postoperative complications and death
following nonemergent general surgical operations.
RESULTS: In total, 294 037 patients were studied, of whom 1771 (0.6%) had
preoperative IS. Patients with IS were older and had more significant
preoperative risk factors and comorbidities. As a result, unadjusted analysis
found that 22 of 23 postoperative complications were significantly more likely to
occur in patients with IS. Within the matched cohort, rates of postoperative
pneumonia, ventilator dependence, progressive renal insufficiency, urinary tract 
infection, stroke, venous thromboembolism, and postoperative death continued to
be significantly (P < .05) elevated in patients with IS.
CONCLUSIONS AND RELEVANCE: Impaired sensorium significantly increases
postoperative morbidity and mortality independent of other preoperative risk
factors and comorbidities following nonemergent general surgical operations.
Incorporation of impaired cognitive function into routine preoperative risk
assessment and decision making could be an important addition to traditional risk
assessment strategies.

DOI: 10.1001/jamasurg.2014.863 
PMID: 25409305  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


12. J Atr Fibrillation. 2014 Apr 30;6(6):1042. doi: 10.4022/jafib.1042. eCollection
2014 Apr-May.

Stroke And Bleeding Risk Assessment: Where Are We Now?

Dzeshka MS(1), Lip GY(2).

Author information: 
(1)University of Birmingham Centre for Cardiovascular Sciences City Hospital,
Birmingham B18 7QH, United Kingdom; Grodno State Medical University, Grodno,
Belarus.
(2)University of Birmingham Centre for Cardiovascular Sciences City Hospital,
Birmingham B18 7QH, United Kingdom.

Atrial fibrillation (AF) is one of major problems of the contemporary cardiology.
Ischaemic stroke is a common complication of the AF, and effective prophylaxis
requires treatment with oral anticoagulants. The purpose of this current review
article is to provide an overview of the various stroke and bleeding risk
assessment scores that help decision making with respect to thromboprophylaxis.
Particular focus is made on the currently guideline-recommended stroke and
bleeding risk scores, such as CHA2DS2-VASc (congestive heart failure or left
ventricular dysfunction, hypertension, age ≥75, diabetes, stroke, vascular
disease, age 65-74 and sex category [female]) and HAS-BLED (uncontrolled
hypertension, abnormal renal/liver function, stroke, bleeding history or
predisposition, labile international normalized ratio, elderly [e.g. age >65,
frail condition], drugs [e.g. aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory
drugs]/excessive alcohol) is made. Future directions for improvement of
predictive ability of risk assessment with clinical factors and biomarkers are
also discussed.

DOI: 10.4022/jafib.1042 
PMCID: PMC5135240
PMID: 27957063 


13. Clin Geriatr Med. 2014 May;30(2):279-84. doi: 10.1016/j.cger.2014.01.006. Epub
2014 Mar 4.

Management of postoperative complications: anemia.

Willett LR(1), Carson JL(2).

Author information: 
(1)Division of Education, Rutgers Robert Wood Johnson Medical School, 1 RWJ
Place, MEB-486, New Brunswick, NJ 08903, USA. Electronic address:
willetlr@rwjms.rutgers.edu.
(2)Division of General Internal Medicine, Rutgers Robert Wood Johnson Medical
School, 125 Paterson Street, New Brunswick, NJ 08901, USA. Electronic address:
jeffrey.carson@rutgers.edu.

Anemia is extremely common following hip fracture. Consistent data from
randomized trials show that transfusion of less blood, with a transfusion
threshold around 8 g/dL hemoglobin concentration, is preferable to a traditional 
threshold of 10 g/dL. Adoption of a lower threshold leads to at least equivalent 
clinical outcomes, with much less exposure to transfusion costs and risks. The
most common complication of transfusion is circulatory overload. Future research 
may elucidate the optimal transfusion threshold for these elderly patients and
address the specific needs of subgroups of patients, including those with acute
coronary syndrome or chronic kidney disease.

Copyright © 2014 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.cger.2014.01.006 
PMID: 24721367  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


14. J Vasc Interv Radiol. 2014 Jun;25(6):895-903. doi: 10.1016/j.jvir.2014.01.023.
Epub 2014 Mar 13.

Fluoroscopic versus laparoscopic implantation of peritoneal dialysis catheters: a
retrospective cohort study.

Maher E(1), Wolley MJ(1), Abbas SA(1), Hawkins SP(2), Marshall MR(3).

Author information: 
(1)Departments of Renal Medicine, Middlemore Hospital, Counties Manukau District 
Health Board, P.O. Box 37968, Auckland 1151, New Zealand.
(2)Radiology, Middlemore Hospital, Counties Manukau District Health Board, P.O.
Box 37968, Auckland 1151, New Zealand.
(3)Departments of Renal Medicine, Middlemore Hospital, Counties Manukau District 
Health Board, P.O. Box 37968, Auckland 1151, New Zealand; Faculty of Medical and 
Health Sciences, University of Auckland, Auckland, New Zealand. Electronic
address: mrmarsh@woosh.co.nz.

PURPOSE: A previous clinical trial showed that radiologic insertion of first
peritoneal dialysis (PD) catheters by modified Seldinger technique is noninferior
to laparoscopic surgery in patients at low risk in a clinical trial setting. The 
present cohort study was performed to confirm clinical effectiveness of
radiologic insertion in everyday practice, including insertion in patients with
expanded eligibility criteria and by fellows in training.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Between 2004 and 2009, 286 PD catheters were inserted in
249 patients, 133 with fluoroscopic guidance in the radiology department and 153 
by laparoscopic surgery. Survival analyses were performed with the primary
outcome of complication-free catheter survival and secondary outcomes of overall 
catheter survival and patient survival. Outcomes were assessed at last follow-up,
as long as 365 days after PD catheter insertion.
RESULTS: In the radiologic group, unadjusted 365-day complication-free catheter, 
overall catheter, and patient survival rates were 22.6%, 81.2%, and 82.7%,
respectively, compared with 22.9% (P = .52), 76.5% (P = .4), and 92.8% (P = .01),
respectively, in the laparoscopic group. Frequencies of individual complications 
were similar between groups. Adjusting for patient age, comorbidity, and previous
PD catheter, the hazard ratio (HR) for catheter complications by radiologic
versus laparoscopic insertion is 0.90 (95% confidence interval [CI], 0.62-1.31); 
the HR for overall catheter survival is 1.25 (95% CI, 0.59-2.65); and that for
death is 2.47 (95% CI, 0.84-7.3).
CONCLUSIONS: Radiologic PD catheter insertion is a clinically effective
alternative to laparoscopic surgery, although there was poorer long-term survival
with radiologic catheter placement, possibly because of preferential selection of
radiologic insertion for more frail patients.

Copyright © 2014. Published by Elsevier Inc.

DOI: 10.1016/j.jvir.2014.01.023 
PMID: 24630750  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


15. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2014 Mar;472(3):1010-7. doi: 10.1007/s11999-013-3334-7.
Epub 2013 Oct 29.

Association of a modified frailty index with mortality after femoral neck
fracture in patients aged 60 years and older.

Patel KV(1), Brennan KL, Brennan ML, Jupiter DC, Shar A, Davis ML.

Author information: 
(1)Department of Orthopaedics, Scott and White Memorial Hospital, 2401 S 31st
Street, Temple, TX, 76508, USA, kpatel@sw.org.

Comment in
    Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2014 Mar;472(3):1018-9.

BACKGROUND: Frailty, a multidimensional syndrome entailing loss of energy,
physical ability, cognition, and health, plays a significant role in elderly
morbidity and mortality. No study has examined frailty in relation to mortality
after femoral neck fractures in elderly patients.
QUESTIONS/PURPOSES: We examined the association of a modified frailty index
abbreviated from the Canadian Study of Health and Aging Frailty Index to 1- and
2-year mortality rates after a femoral neck fracture. Specifically we examined:
(1) Is there an association of a modified frailty index with 1- and 2-year
mortality rates in patients aged 60 years and older who sustain a low-energy
femoral neck fracture? (2) Do the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves 
indicate that the modified frailty index can be a potential tool predictive of
mortality and does a specific modified frailty index value demonstrate increased 
odds ratio for mortality? (3) Do any of the individual clinical deficits
comprising the modified frailty index independently associate with mortality?
METHODS: We retrospectively reviewed 697 low-energy femoral neck fractures in
patients aged 60 years and older at our Level I trauma center from 2005 to 2009. 
A total of 218 (31%) patients with high-energy or pathologic fracture,
postoperative complication including infection or revision surgery, fracture of
the contralateral hip, or missing documented mobility status were excluded. The
remaining 481 patients, with a mean age of 81.2 years, were included. Mortality
data were obtained from a state vital statistics department using date of birth
and Social Security numbers. Statistical analysis included unequal variance
t-test, Pearson correlation of age and frailty, ROC curves and area under the
curve, Hosmer-Lemeshow statistics, and logistic regression models.
RESULTS: One-year mortality analysis found the mean modified frailty index was
higher in patients who died (4.6 ± 1.8) than in those who lived (3.0 ± 2; p <
0.001), which was maintained in a 2-year mortality analysis (4.4 ± 1.8 versus 3.0
± 2; p < 0.001). In ROC analysis, the area under the curve was 0.74 and 0.72 for 
1- and 2-year mortality, respectively. Patients with a modified frailty index of 
4 or greater had an odds ratio of 4.97 for 1-year mortality and an odds ratio of 
4.01 for 2-year mortality as compared with patients with less than 4. Logistic
regression models demonstrated that the clinical deficits of mobility,
respiratory, renal, malignancy, thyroid, and impaired cognition were
independently associated with 1- and 2-year mortality.
CONCLUSIONS: Patients aged 60 years and older sustaining a femoral neck fracture,
with a higher modified frailty index, had increased 1- and 2-year mortality
rates, and the ROC analysis suggests that this tool may be predictive of
mortality. Patients with a modified frailty index of 4 or greater have increased 
risk for mortality at 1 and 2 years. Clinical deficits of mobility, respiratory, 
renal, malignancy, thyroid, and impaired cognition also may be independently
associated with mortality. The modified frailty index may be a useful tool in
predicting mortality, guiding patient and family expectations and elucidating
implant/surgery choices. Further prospective studies are necessary to strengthen 
the predictive power of the index.
LEVEL OF EVIDENCE: Level IV, prognostic study. See Instructions for Authors for a
complete description of levels of evidence.

DOI: 10.1007/s11999-013-3334-7 
PMCID: PMC3916591
PMID: 24166073  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


16. Injury. 2013 Dec;44(12):1945-8. doi: 10.1016/j.injury.2013.07.023. Epub 2013 Aug 
6.

Incidence of periprosthetic fractures after hip hemiarthroplasty: Are uncemented 
prostheses unsafe?

McGraw IW(1), Spence SC, Baird EJ, Eckhardt SM, Ayana GE.

Author information: 
(1)Department of Trauma & Orthopaedics, Royal Alexandra Hospital, Paisley,
Scotland PA2 9PN, UK. Electronic address: iainmcgraw@gmail.com.

Displaced intracapsular fractures of the neck of femur are routinely treated in
the elderly with either cemented or uncemented hemiarthroplasty. Recent evidence 
suggests a superior outcome with the use of cement, but uncemented prostheses are
still employed for those with multiple co-morbidities or particular frailty. In
Scotland, the Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network (SIGN) recommendations 
are used to identify which patients should receive a cemented prosthesis. These
are simply based upon the presence of cardiorespiratory disease, particularly in 
the frail elderly patient. Between January 2007 and June 2010, a total of 1397
patients with neck-of-femur fractures presented to our unit. Retrospective
analysis was performed with particular attention given to the rate of
postoperative periprosthetic fracture. As many as 546 fractures were treated with
hemiarthroplasty, of which 183 were treated with a cemented Exeter Trauma Stem
(ETS) and 363 were treated with an uncemented Austin-Moore prosthesis (AMP). At
the time of our retrospective analysis, we found that 15 (4%) patients treated
with an uncemented prosthesis went on to sustain a periprosthetic fracture. There
were no periprosthetic fractures in the cemented group (p=0.004). Data analysis
by case-note review of those patients sustaining a periprosthetic fracture was
then performed. Seven (50%) suffered from confusion secondary to dementia, six
(43%) had a history of significant cardiac disease (recent myocardial infarction 
(MI) or cardiac failure) and two (14%) had known renal impairment. The mean time 
to fracture after uncemented hemiarthroplasty was 2 years. The majority (80%)
were fractures which required further surgery. Revision surgery in these patients
was associated with an overall complication rate of 42% (mainly deep infection
and haemorrhage requiring transfusion). Two of the patients had a fracture that
could be treated conservatively. It is concluded that, in conjunction with the
treating senior anaesthetist, cemented implants should be considered in all
patients, especially those who are deemed to be frail and with multiple
co-morbidities. A periprosthetic fracture rate of 14% at a mean of 2 years after 
uncemented hemiarthroplasty represents a potentially unacceptable risk for such a
frail population. In particular, we feel that the AMP should not be used for
treating displaced intracapsular neck-of-femur fractures.

Copyright © 2013 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.injury.2013.07.023 
PMID: 24001784  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


17. Injury. 2013 Dec;44(12):1919-25. doi: 10.1016/j.injury.2013.05.012. Epub 2013 Jun
18.

Re-admission to Level 2 unit after hip-fracture surgery - Risk factors, reasons
and outcome.

Buecking B(1), Eschbach D, Koutras C, Kratz T, Balzer-Geldsetzer M, Dodel R,
Ruchholtz S.

Author information: 
(1)Department of Trauma, Hand and Reconstructive Surgery, University of Giessen
and Marburg, Baldingerstrasse, 35043 Marburg, Germany. Electronic address:
buecking@med.uni-marburg.de.

INTRODUCTION: Hip fractures are common geriatric fractures with increasing
incidence. Treatment of these fractures is still associated with high rates of
complications and poor outcome. Data concerning unexpected re-admission to a
Level 2 unit after an initial inconspicuous postoperative course are limited. We 
aimed to identify causes and associated risk factors for admission as well as
impact of re-admission on acute care and short-term outcome.
PATIENTS AND METHODS: Patients over 60 years of age with hip fractures were
included in this prospective single-centre observational study. Patients with
polytrauma or malignancy-associated fractures were excluded. Age, gender,
fracture type, pre-fracture residential, physical and cognitive status, recording
to the American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) score, Barthel Index (BI) and 
Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) were recorded on admission. Date, type of
surgery and operation time were evaluated. Postoperatively, the prevalence of and
reasons for unexpected re-admission to the Level 2 unit and patients' outcome
were measured. Parameters were hospital mortality, BI at discharge, length of
stay in hospital and type of discharge. Univariate and multivariate analyses were
performed to identify risk factors for admission to the Level 2 unit and
influence on patients' outcome.
RESULTS: Out of 402 included patients, 48 (12%) were re-admitted to the Level 2
unit. The most frequent reasons were non-surgical (n=38), such as respiratory
failure (n=12), cardiovascular diseases (n=8) and acute renal failure (n=5). Ten 
patients were re-admitted due to a revision surgery of the hip. We identified two
independent risk factors for readmission: male gender (odds ratio (OR)=2.38,
confidence interval (95% CI)=1.10-5.15, p=0.027) and type of fracture, especially
femoral neck fracture (OR=7.40, 95% CI=2.39-23.26, p=0.001). Patients who were
re-admitted to the Level 2 unit had a higher mortality (β=2.09, OR=8.07, 95%
CI=2.44-26.75, p=0.001), an increase in hospital stay (β=7.0, 95% CI 5.2-8.7,
p<0.001) and a lower functional outcome (BI, β=-17, 95% CI=-23 to -10, p<0.001).
CONCLUSION: Unexpected admission to the Level 2 unit in the post-surgical period 
is a frequent phenomenon in geriatric hip-fracture patients. Males and femoral
neck fracture patients seem to be especially endangered. Although the majority of
reasons for admissions were not immediately life-threatening illnesses, they had 
a substantial negative impact on patients' outcome. This emphasises the
importance of careful handling of this frail patient population.

Copyright © 2013 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.injury.2013.05.012 
PMID: 23791011  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


18. Eur J Intern Med. 2013 Jun;24(4):285-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ejim.2013.02.001. Epub
2013 Mar 15.

Thromboprophylaxis in the oldest old with atrial fibrillation: between Scylla and
Charybdis.

Mannucci PM(1).

Author information: 
(1)Scientific Direction, IRCCS Maggiore Policlinico Hospital Foundation, Milan,
Italy. pmmannucci@libero.it

Comment in
    Eur J Intern Med. 2014 Feb;25(2):e22.

Within a few decades half of the patients with non-valvular atrial fibrillation
(AF) will be older than 80 years. These patients are at particularly high risk of
thromboembolism (Scylla) but also of the hemorrhagic complications of
thromboprophylaxis (Charybdis). A frequent compromise is to use as antithrombotic
agents instead of vitamin-K antagonists aspirin or other antiplatelet drugs,
which are ineffective for thromboprophylaxis in the oldest old and definitely not
free from a high risk of severe bleeding. All the new direct anticoagulants
currently licensed (dabigatran, rivaroxaban, apixaban) are at least as effective 
as warfarin for thromboprophylaxis in AF, but the risk of the intracranial
bleeding, the most feared complication of anticoagulant therapy, is at least
halved. In the oldest patients of 80 years of age or more preliminary data,
available so far only for dabigatran, indicate that the favorable outcomes of
direct anticoagulants are also present in this subgroup, often left untreated for
fear of intracranial bleeding. The choice between the different direct
anticoagulants is driven by the presence or not of renal insufficiency, the
presence and degree of multimorbidity and polypharmacy and by the likelihood or
not of poor treatment adherence in patients who are often frail and with some
degree of cognitive impairment.

Copyright © 2013 European Federation of Internal Medicine. Published by Elsevier 
B.V. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.ejim.2013.02.001 
PMID: 23499350  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


19. Heart Surg Forum. 2013 Feb 1;16(1):E21-3. doi: 10.1532/HSF98.20121075.

Mitral paravalvular leak: caution in percutaneous occluder device deployment.

Altarabsheh SE(1), Deo SV, Rihal CS, Park SJ.

Author information: 
(1)Division of Cardiovascular Surgery, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN 55905, USA.

A frail 70-year-old woman presented with symptomatic mitral paravalvular leak 2
months after undergoing a double valve replacement for mixed mitral and aortic
valve disease. There was no evidence of prosthetic valve endocarditis.
Percutaneous closure of the paravalvular leak was attempted as an alternative to 
a high-risk surgical procedure. This therapy was successful in reducing the
regurgitation but resulted in severe intravascular hemolysis and acute renal
failure requiring hemodialysis.The development of new hemolysis and acute renal
failure directed our attention to the Amplatzer device as a possible etiology for
these complications. The assumption that her kidney injury was recent and likely 
reversible compelled us to think of the surgical method as a definitive option. A
re-operative surgery was performed, which included retrieval of the occluder
devices, pericardial patch repair, and re-replacement using a new biological
prosthesis. The patient's urine output gradually improved, and the patient was
dismissed with normal renal function.We present this case as an unusual
complication of percutaneous device closure. It also highlights the reversible
nature of acute renal failure due to intravascular hemolysis and demonstrates the
importance of early surgical intervention for this condition.

DOI: 10.1532/HSF98.20121075 
PMID: 23439352  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


20. Best Pract Res Clin Anaesthesiol. 2011 Sep;25(3):319-27. doi:
10.1016/j.bpa.2011.05.003.

Postoperative mortality and complications.

Story DA(1).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Health, Victoria, Australia.
David.Story@austin.org.au

Recent publications not only underline the risks of age and disease during
surgery but also help us quantify the risks with greater precision. Importantly, 
patient factors often have a stronger association with postoperative mortality
than surgical factors. Important factors preoperatively are: age, American
Society of Anaesthesiologist (ASA) physical status, emergency surgery, and plasma
albumin concentration. There is emerging work on quantifying frailty as a further
risk factor for perioperative complication and mortality as well as need for
higher level of care after discharge from hospital. Important postoperative
complications include sepsis and kidney injury. Preventing, detecting and
managing complications and mortality is the greatest challenge facing those
caring for surgical patients, including anaesthetists. Evidence for the long term
effects of perioperative complications adds further importance to minimizing
perioperative complications. Newer approaches in patient care, particularly
co-management during the postoperative phase by different specialities are
emerging. Managing high-risk patients should also be enhanced with greater
surveillance and more rapid and appropriate response; ensuring we do not fail to 
rescue our patients.

2011 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.bpa.2011.05.003 
PMID: 21925399  [Indexed for MEDLINE]

