//(frail AND (frail OR phenotype OR index)) AND ("chronic kidney disease" OR "chronic renal disease" OR "chronic kidney insufficiency" OR "chronic renal insufficiency" OR "kidney transplant" OR "renal transplant" OR "end-stage kidney disease" OR "end-stage renal disease") AND complication
//
1. Langenbecks Arch Surg. 2018 Dec;403(8):999-1005. doi: 10.1007/s00423-018-1726-6. 
Epub 2018 Nov 10.

Safety and efficacy of subtotal or total parathyroidectomy for patients with
secondary or tertiary hyperparathyroidism in four academic centers in the
Netherlands.

van der Plas WY(1), Dulfer RR(2), Koh EY(3), Vogt L(4), Appelman-Dijkstra NM(5), 
Schepers A(6), Rotmans JI(7), Pol RA(1), van Ginhoven TM(2), Hoorn EJ(8), Nieveen
van Dijkum EJM(3), Engelsman AF(3), de Borst MH(9), Kruijff S(10); Dutch
Hyperparathyroidism Study Group (DHSG).

Author information: 
(1)Department of Surgery, University Medical Center Groningen, University of
Groningen, Hanzeplein 1, 9700 RB, Groningen, The Netherlands.
(2)Department of Surgery, Erasmus Medical Center, Erasmus University Rotteredam, 
Rotterdam, The Netherlands.
(3)Department of Surgery, Amsterdam UMC, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The 
Netherlands.
(4)Department of Nephrology, Amsterdam UMC, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam,
The Netherlands.
(5)Department of Endocrinology, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden
University, Leiden, The Netherlands.
(6)Department of Surgery, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden University,
Leiden, The Netherlands.
(7)Department of Internal Medicine, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden
University, Leiden, The Netherlands.
(8)Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Nephrology and Transplantation,
Erasmus Medical Center, Rotterdam, The Netherlands.
(9)Department of Nephrology, University Medical Center Groningen, University of
Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands.
(10)Department of Surgery, University Medical Center Groningen, University of
Groningen, Hanzeplein 1, 9700 RB, Groningen, The Netherlands. s.kruijff@umcg.nl.

PURPOSE: Hyperparathyroidism (HPT) is a common abnormality in patients with
end-stage renal disease (ESRD). Since the introduction of cinacalcet in 2004, a
shift from surgery toward predominantly medical treatment has occurred. Surgery
is thought to be associated with more complications than oral medication. The aim
of this retrospective study was to evaluate 30-day outcomes and effectiveness of 
parathyroidectomy (PTx) in ESRD patients in the Netherlands.
METHODS: A national database containing data from four academic medical centers
in the Netherlands of patients with ESRD-related HPT, who had undergone PTx and
kidney transplantation between 1994 and 2015, was established. Primary endpoints 
were 30-day mortality and complication rate. Secondary endpoints were biochemical
measurements.
RESULTS: We identified 187 HPT patients undergoing PTx, with a median age of
46 years. Median preoperative PTH level was 866 pg/mL (interquartile range [IQR] 
407-1547 pg/mL). At 3 months, the median PTH drop from baseline was 93% (IQR,
71-98%) to a median of 61 pg/mL (IQR, 23-148 pg/mL, p < 0.001). Over the 25-year 
inclusion period, 13 patients (7.0%) required re-exploration for persistent or
recurrent disease. Thirty-day mortality and complication rate were 0.0% and 7.9% 
respectively. Median serum calcium levels improved significantly postoperatively 
from 2.6 (2.4-2.8) mmol/L to 2.3 (2.1-2.5) mmol/L (p < 0.001).
CONCLUSIONS: PTx is a safe and effective procedure in the frail ESRD population. 
These data show that there should be no reluctance for surgical intervention and 
when indicated, nephrologists can safely refer these patients for PTx.

DOI: 10.1007/s00423-018-1726-6 
PMCID: PMC6328516
PMID: 30415287 


2. J Frailty Aging. 2017;6(2):103-106. doi: 10.14283/jfa.2017.14.

Frailty in End-Stage Renal Disease Patients under Dialysis and Its Association
with Clinical and Biochemical Markers.

Poveda V(1), Filgueiras M, Miranda V, Santos-Silva A, Paúl C, Costa E.

Author information: 
(1)Elísio Costa, Laboratório de Bioquímica, Departamento de Ciências Biológicas, 
Universidade do Porto, Rua de Jorge Viterbo Ferreira, 228, 4050-313 Porto,
Portugal, Email: emcosta@ff.up.pt.

Frailty is a common complication in elderly patients with end-stage renal disease
(ESRD) under dialysis, which is a strong risk factor for low quality of life,
morbidity, and mortality. In this work, we aimed to evaluate the prevalence of
frailty in a group of Portuguese ESRD patients, and its association with
socio-demographic, clinical and biochemical markers. We performed a
cross-sectional study with 83 ESRD patients (44 males and 39 females, 64.3
[±14.6] years old) on regular dialysis. The classification of the ESRD patients
as robust, pre-frail and frail was performed using the FRAIL questionnaire.
Social support, data about sociodemographic and comorbidities, and
haematological, iron status, dialysis adequacy, nutritional and inflammatory
markers were also evaluated. Our results confirmed that frailty is a highly
prevalent condition in ESRD patients, particularly in female patients. An
association between FRAIL score and increased depressive symptoms, presence of
hypertension and decrease nutritional status was also found.

DOI: 10.14283/jfa.2017.14 
PMID: 28555712  [Indexed for MEDLINE]

Conflict of interest statement: none


3. Ann Vasc Surg. 2016 Aug;35:19-29. doi: 10.1016/j.avsg.2016.01.052. Epub 2016 Jun 
2.

Preoperative Frailty Increases Risk of Nonhome Discharge after Elective Vascular 
Surgery in Home-Dwelling Patients.

Arya S(1), Long CA(2), Brahmbhatt R(2), Shafii S(2), Brewster LP(3), Veeraswamy
R(2), Johnson TM 2nd(4), Johanning JM(5).

Author information: 
(1)Division of Vascular Surgery, Department of Surgery, Emory University School
of Medicine, Atlanta, GA; Surgical Service Line, Atlanta VA Medical Center,
Decatur, GA. Electronic address: shipra.arya@emory.edu.
(2)Division of Vascular Surgery, Department of Surgery, Emory University School
of Medicine, Atlanta, GA.
(3)Division of Vascular Surgery, Department of Surgery, Emory University School
of Medicine, Atlanta, GA; Surgical Service Line, Atlanta VA Medical Center,
Decatur, GA.
(4)Division of General Medicine and Geriatrics, Department of Medicine, Emory
University School of Medicine.
(5)Division of Vascular Surgery, Department of Surgery, University of Nebraska
Medical Center, Omaha, NE.

BACKGROUND: Patient-centered quality outcomes such as disposition after surgery
are increasingly being scrutinized. Preoperative factors predictive of nonhome
discharge (DC) may identify at-risk patients for targeted interventions. This
study examines the association among preoperative risk factors, frailty, and
nonhome DC after elective vascular surgery procedures in patients living at home.
METHODS: The 2011-2012 National Surgical Quality Improvement Project database was
queried to identify all home-dwelling patients who underwent elective vascular
procedures (endovascular and open aortic aneurysm repair, suprainguinal and
infrainguinal bypasses, peripheral endovascular interventions, carotid
endarterectomy, and stent). Preoperative frailty was measured using the modified 
frailty index (mFI; derived from Canadian Study of Health and Aging). Univariate 
and multivariate logistic regression analysis was performed to examine the
association of frailty and nonhome DC.
RESULTS: Of 15,843 home-dwelling patients, 1,177 patients (7.4%) did not return
home postoperatively. Frailty (mFI > 0.25) conferred a significantly increased
2-fold risk of nonhome DC disposition for each procedure type. Frailty, female
gender, open procedures, increasing age, end-stage renal disease, and occurrence 
of any postoperative complication were associated with increased risk of nonhome 
DC. On multivariate logistic regression analysis, frailty increased the odds of
nonhome DC by 60% (odds ratio 1.6, 95% confidence interval 1.4-1.8) after
adjusting for other covariates. In the presence of complications, the risk of
nonhome DC was 27.5% in frail versus 16.5% in nonfrail patients (P < 0.001). In
the absence of complications, although absolute risk was lower, frail patients
were nearly twice as likely to not return home (frail 5.5% vs. nonfrail 2.75%,
P < 0.001).
CONCLUSIONS: Frail home-dwelling patients undergoing elective vascular procedures
are at high risk of not returning home after surgery. Preoperative frailty
assessment appears to hold potential for counseling regarding postsurgery
disposition and DC planning.

Published by Elsevier Inc.

DOI: 10.1016/j.avsg.2016.01.052 
PMID: 27263810  [Indexed for MEDLINE]


4. Clin Geriatr Med. 2014 May;30(2):279-84. doi: 10.1016/j.cger.2014.01.006. Epub
2014 Mar 4.

Management of postoperative complications: anemia.

Willett LR(1), Carson JL(2).

Author information: 
(1)Division of Education, Rutgers Robert Wood Johnson Medical School, 1 RWJ
Place, MEB-486, New Brunswick, NJ 08903, USA. Electronic address:
willetlr@rwjms.rutgers.edu.
(2)Division of General Internal Medicine, Rutgers Robert Wood Johnson Medical
School, 125 Paterson Street, New Brunswick, NJ 08901, USA. Electronic address:
jeffrey.carson@rutgers.edu.

Anemia is extremely common following hip fracture. Consistent data from
randomized trials show that transfusion of less blood, with a transfusion
threshold around 8 g/dL hemoglobin concentration, is preferable to a traditional 
threshold of 10 g/dL. Adoption of a lower threshold leads to at least equivalent 
clinical outcomes, with much less exposure to transfusion costs and risks. The
most common complication of transfusion is circulatory overload. Future research 
may elucidate the optimal transfusion threshold for these elderly patients and
address the specific needs of subgroups of patients, including those with acute
coronary syndrome or chronic kidney disease.

Copyright © 2014 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.

DOI: 10.1016/j.cger.2014.01.006 
PMID: 24721367  [Indexed for MEDLINE]
