<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><xml><records><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Chao, Chia-Ter</author><author>Huang, Jenq-Wen</author><author>Huang, Sheng-Jean</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>SIMPLE FRAIL SCALE OUTPERFORMS OTHER FRAILTY INSTRUMENTS REGARDING DIALYSIS COMPLICATIONS IN RURAL CHRONIC DIALYSIS PATIENTS</title><secondary-title>NEPHROLOGY DIALYSIS TRANSPLANTATION</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>NEPHROLOGY DIALYSIS TRANSPLANTATION</full-title></periodical><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2015</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1093/ndt/gfv183.79</electronic-resource-num><notes>read
.
Multivariate linear regression analysis confirmed an independently negative association between serum albumin and the simple FRAIL scale scores ( p = 0.01).
.
52nd Congress of the
European-Renal-Association-European-Dialysis-and-Transplant-Assocation,
London, ENGLAND, MAY 28-31, 2015</notes><research-notes>read
.
Multivariate linear regression analysis confirmed an independently negative association between serum albumin and the simple FRAIL scale scores ( p = 0.01).
.
52nd Congress of the
European-Renal-Association-European-Dialysis-and-Transplant-Assocation,
London, ENGLAND, MAY 28-31, 2015</research-notes><urls/><abstract>Introduction and Aims: Frailty has been recognized as an important geriatric outcome predictor. However, few studies focus on its influence on rural patients undergoing chronic dialysis. Comparison of different self-report questionnaires for frailty assessment among these patients has not been attempted before. Methods: A prospectively enrolled rural chronic dialysis cohort was used for analysis. Six types of self-report questionnaires were administered to these patients. Correlation analyses between questionnaire results and clinical parameters/dialysis complications, including anemia, inflammation, and dyselectrolytemia were performed. Variables demonstrating significant correlations were further tested in multiple regression analyses to determine their associations. Results: Six types of questionnaire (Strawbridge questionnaire, Edmonton Frail Scale, simple FRAIL scale, Groningen Frail Indicator, G8 questionnaire, and Tilburg Frail Indicator) were provided to rural patients undergoing chronic dialysis. Scores from each questionnaire were significantly associated with each other, except the G8 questionnaire. Scores from the simple FRAIL scale correlated significantly with age (p = 0.02), female gender (p = 0.03), higher Liu’s comorbidity index (p = 0.02), lower serum albumin (p = 0.03) and creatinine levels (p &lt; 0.01), and higher ferritin levels (p = 0.02) (figure). The other 5 questionnaires did not show consistently significant relationships with important dialysis-related complications. Multivariate linear regression analysis confirmed an independently negative association between serum albumin and the simple FRAIL scale scores (p = 0.01). Conclusions: This is the first study establishing the utility of different self-report questionnaires for assessing frailty in chronic dialysis patients. This simple FRAIL scale demonstrated a stronger relationship with important dialysis-related complications.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>EM, Abdel-Rahman</author><author>Mansour, W</author><author>JL, Holley</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Thyroid hormone abnormalities and frailty in elderly patients with chronic kidney disease: a hypothesis.</title><secondary-title>Seminars in Dialysis</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Seminars in Dialysis</full-title></periodical><pages>317-323</pages><volume>23</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords><keyword>Aged</keyword><keyword>Aged, 80 and Over</keyword><keyword>Frail Elderly</keyword><keyword>Incidence</keyword><keyword>Kidney Failure, Chronic -- Blood</keyword><keyword>Kidney Failure, Chronic -- Complications</keyword><keyword>Risk Factors</keyword><keyword>Thyroid Diseases -- Blood</keyword><keyword>Thyroid Diseases -- Complications</keyword><keyword>Thyroid Diseases -- Epidemiology</keyword><keyword>Thyroid Hormones -- Blood</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2010</year></dates><pub-location>Division of Nephrology, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA. ea6n@virginia.edu</pub-location><publisher>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1111/j.1525-139X.2010.00736.x</electronic-resource-num><notes>hypothesis

.

Accession Number: 105061858. Language: English. Entry Date: 20101112. Revision Date: 20150711. Publication Type: Journal Article. Journal Subset: Biomedical; USA. NLM UID: 8911629.</notes><research-notes>hypothesis

.

Accession Number: 105061858. Language: English. Entry Date: 20101112. Revision Date: 20150711. Publication Type: Journal Article. Journal Subset: Biomedical; USA. NLM UID: 8911629.</research-notes><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://EM, Mansour, JL - 2010 - Thyroid hormone abnormalities and frailty in elderly patients with chronic kidney disease a hypothesis._2010_may</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=cin20&amp;AN=105061858&amp;site=ehost-live&amp;scope=site</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Thyroid hormones play a crucial role in the metabolic activities of adults, affecting almost every organ system. All types of thyroid diseases are encountered in the elderly. As symptoms and signs of thyroid diseases may overlap with what is considered to be “normal aging,” the presence of a thyroid disorder may go undiagnosed in the elderly. This potential problem is further compounded in elderly patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD), where the presence of an underlying hormonal problem such as hypothyroidism may be erroneously attributed to multiple comorbidities, the aging process, or the kidney disease. Frailty is being recognized as a contributing factor to the poor outcomes (hospitalization and high mortality) in elderly patients with CKD. Predisposing factors leading to frailty in elderly with CKD such as increased inflammatory markers, anemia, low testosterone, sarcopenia, and depression are associated with thyroid hormonal abnormalities. These associations are remarkable and raise the question of whether routine monitoring and screening for thyroid hormone changes in elderly CKD patients might be helpful in identifying reversible causes of frailty. In this review, we will focus on the associations between thyroid hormone abnormalities and the predisposing factors of frailty in elderly patients with CKD. If a cause–effect relationship of thyroid hormone abnormalities and factors predisposing to frailty in CKD patients is established, identification and treatment of thyroid abnormalities in this population would assume increased importance.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">3</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Johansen, Kirsten L</author><author>Delgado, Cynthia</author><author>Bao, Yeran</author><author>Tamura, Manjula Kurella</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Frailty and dialysis initiation</title><secondary-title>Seminars in dialysis</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Seminars in dialysis</full-title></periodical><pages>690-696</pages><volume>26</volume><issue>6</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2013</year></dates><publisher>Wiley Online Library</publisher><isbn>0894-0959</isbn><notes>read
.
early dialysis initiation

(descriptive)
.
※只說符合一些條件時，會有較早的dialysis initiation。而這些條件剛好是frailty的components。</notes><research-notes>read
.
early dialysis initiation

(descriptive)
.
※只說符合一些條件時，會有較早的dialysis initiation。而這些條件剛好是frailty的components。</research-notes><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Johansen et al. - 2013 - Frailty and dialysis initiation.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Lee, S</author><author>Kim, J C</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Frailty as an independent predictor for hospitalization-free survival even in relatively healthy patients receiving chronic dialysis</title><secondary-title>Nephrology dialysis transplantation.</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Nephrology dialysis transplantation.</full-title></periodical><pages>iii316</pages><volume>30</volume><keywords><keyword>*dialysis</keyword><keyword>*edetic acid</keyword><keyword>*hospitalization</keyword><keyword>*human</keyword><keyword>*normal human</keyword><keyword>*patient</keyword><keyword>*survival</keyword><keyword>Blood chemistry</keyword><keyword>Body mass</keyword><keyword>Body weight</keyword><keyword>Chronic kidney disease</keyword><keyword>Confidence interval</keyword><keyword>Death</keyword><keyword>Devices</keyword><keyword>Diabetes mellitus</keyword><keyword>Disability</keyword><keyword>Education</keyword><keyword>Female</keyword><keyword>Follow up</keyword><keyword>Hazard ratio</keyword><keyword>Hemodialysis</keyword><keyword>Hemodialysis patient</keyword><keyword>Informed consent</keyword><keyword>Male</keyword><keyword>Medical record</keyword><keyword>Multivariate logistic regression analysis</keyword><keyword>Peritoneal dialysis</keyword><keyword>Phenotype</keyword><keyword>Physical inactivity</keyword><keyword>Population</keyword><keyword>Prevalence</keyword><keyword>Proportional hazards model</keyword><keyword>Questionnaire</keyword><keyword>Risk</keyword><keyword>Unemployment</keyword><keyword>Univariate analysis</keyword><keyword>Vascular access</keyword><keyword>Weight reduction</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2015</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1093/ndt/gfv183.36</electronic-resource-num><notes>Read,
,
The proportion with hospitalizations was 24.4% for non‐frail, 33.0% for pre‐frail and 48.4% for frail (P&amp;lt; 0.001). On univariate analysis, pre‐frail and frail patients were as 1.4 (95% confidence interval [CI] 1.07 to 1.78) and 2.4 (95% CI 1.86 to 3.07) times as more likely to be hospitalized, respectively. Frail phenotype remained significantly associated with hospitalization (adjusted hazard ratio 1.80; 95% CI 1.4 to 2.3) in multivariate Cox proportional hazards models.</notes><research-notes>Read,
,
The proportion with hospitalizations was 24.4% for non‐frail, 33.0% for pre‐frail and 48.4% for frail (P&amp;lt; 0.001). On univariate analysis, pre‐frail and frail patients were as 1.4 (95% confidence interval [CI] 1.07 to 1.78) and 2.4 (95% CI 1.86 to 3.07) times as more likely to be hospitalized, respectively. Frail phenotype remained significantly associated with hospitalization (adjusted hazard ratio 1.80; 95% CI 1.4 to 2.3) in multivariate Cox proportional hazards models.</research-notes><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://lee2015.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>https://www.cochranelibrary.com/central/doi/10.1002/central/CN-01172992/full</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Introduction and Aims: Frailty is a distinct clinical syndrome beyond just being old and ultimately results in increased risk for disability, hospitalization, and death. Interestingly, it has been reported that frailty is more common and appears even in early stage of chronic kidney disease (CKD) and much younger population of this group compared to the general population. We investigated the prevalence, correlates of frailty and the association of frailty with hospitalization‐free survival among clinically stable patients undergoing maintenance hemodialysis (MHD) and chronic peritoneal dialysis (CPD). Methods: Between July 2012 and December 2012, we recruited study subjects according to the inclusion criteria as follows: (1) age of 20 years or older, (2) at least 6 months or longer on dialysis, (3) no hospitalization for the last 3 months, except for vascular access problem in case of MHD patients, (4) ambulatory patients with or without assistive device, (5) cognitive enough to answer the questionnaires without help from others, and (6) gave informed consent without proxy and finally followed 1,658 patients ( MHD =1,255 and CPD = 403) until August 2014. We adopted frailty phenotype composed of the following components; 1) unintentional weight loss more than 4.5 Kg or 5% of the previous body weight for the last 1 year, 2) physical inactivity, 3) RAND‐36 physical function (PF) scale &lt;75 and vitality scale &lt;55 as surrogates for weakness/slowness and exhaustion, respectively. Low PF scale was scored as 2 points and other components as 1 point for each. Those with 0, 1‐2 and 3 or more points were considered as non‐frail, pre‐frail and frail, respectively. Demographic data were obtained by review of medical records. Blood chemistry data used were the values averaged over the three consecutive routine checkup. Results: The 1,658 participants evaluated were 55.9 +/‐12.9 years of age (mean +/‐ SD) on dialysis for 5.2+/‐4.5 years; 55.7% were male and 39.4% were diabetes. Frail subjects were 577 (34.8 %) and 757 (45.7%) were pre‐frail. Multivariate logistic regression analysis showed that female sex, unemployed status, older age, higher body mass index, lower education level, lower TIBC and comorbid conditions were independently associated with frailty. During the 86 weeks follow‐up period, 608 patients were hospitalized. The proportion with hospitalizations was 24.4% for non‐frail, 33.0% for pre‐frail and 48.4% for frail (P&lt; 0.001). On univariate analysis, pre‐frail and frail patients were as 1.4 (95% confidence interval [CI] 1.07 to 1.78) and 2.4 (95% CI 1.86 to 3.07) times as more likely to be hospitalized, respectively. Frail phenotype remained significantly associated with hospitalization (adjusted hazard ratio 1.80; 95% CI 1.4 to 2.3) in multivariate Cox proportional hazards models. Conclusions: Frailty phenotype was very common and significant predictor of hospitalization‐free survival even in a relatively healthy patients receiving chronic dialysis. More studies are necessary for preventing or attenuating frailty in the chronic dialysis patients.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>López-Soto, Pablo Jesús</author><author>De Giorgi, Alfredo</author><author>Senno, Elisa</author><author>Tiseo, Ruana</author><author>Ferraresi, Annamaria</author><author>Canella, Cinzia</author><author>Rodríguez-Borrego, María Aurora</author><author>Manfredini, Roberto</author><author>Fabbian, Fabio</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Renal disease and accidental falls: a review of published evidence.</title><secondary-title>BMC Nephrology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>BMC Nephrology</full-title></periodical><pages>176</pages><volume>16</volume><keywords><keyword>Accidental Falls/*statistics &amp; numerical data</keyword><keyword>Age Factors</keyword><keyword>Chronic/*epidemiology</keyword><keyword>Chronic/epidemiology</keyword><keyword>Humans</keyword><keyword>Kidney Failure</keyword><keyword>Recurrence</keyword><keyword>Renal Insufficiency</keyword><keyword>Risk Factors</keyword><keyword>Sex Factors</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2015</year></dates><pub-location>Department of Nursing, The Maimonides Institute for Biomedical Research in Cordoba, University of Córdoba, University Hospital Reina Sofía of Córdoba, Córdoba, Spain. pablolopezsoto90@gmail.com.</pub-location><publisher>BioMed Central</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1186/s12882-015-0173-7</electronic-resource-num><notes>read
.
falls in frail older adults on hemodialysis.

.

Accession Number: 26510510. Language: English. Date Revised: 20190108. Date Created: 20151030. Date Completed: 20160629. Update Code: 20190108. Publication Type: Journal Article. Journal ID: 100967793. Publication Model: Electronic. Cited Medium: Internet. NLM ISO Abbr: BMC Nephrol. Linking ISSN: 14712369. Subset: IM; Date of Electronic Publication: 2015 Oct 29. ; Original Imprints: Publication: London : BioMed Central, [2000-</notes><research-notes>read
.
falls in frail older adults on hemodialysis.

.

Accession Number: 26510510. Language: English. Date Revised: 20190108. Date Created: 20151030. Date Completed: 20160629. Update Code: 20190108. Publication Type: Journal Article. Journal ID: 100967793. Publication Model: Electronic. Cited Medium: Internet. NLM ISO Abbr: BMC Nephrol. Linking ISSN: 14712369. Subset: IM; Date of Electronic Publication: 2015 Oct 29. ; Original Imprints: Publication: London : BioMed Central, [2000-</research-notes><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://10.1186@s12882-015-0173-7.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=cmedm&amp;AN=26510510&amp;site=ehost-live&amp;scope=site</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Background: The pathogenesis of falling is complex, and identification of risk factors may be essential for prevention. The relationship between renal disease and falls is unclear, and the goal of this study was to collect the available evidence and investigate the relationship between accidental falls and renal dysfunction.; Methods: Electronic searches were performed in the MEDLINE, Scopus, Ovid SP and Web of Science databases to identify the appropriate literature. The themes used were: falls (combined in the title/abstract fall or falls or falling or faller* or fallen or slip* or trip* or (MeSH) accidental falls) and renal insufficiency (chronic or renal insufficiency or kidney diseases combined in title/abstract renal disease* or kidney disease* or renal insufficiency or kidney insufficiency or kidney failure or renal failure or MeSH renal insufficiency, chronic or renal insufficiency or kidney diseases). The incidence, risk factors, complications, and characteristics of the falls were analyzed.; Results: Eight prospective cohorts including five cross-sectional studies, and one case-control study were identified. No randomized controlled studies were found. The incidence of falls in chronic kidney disease patients ranged between 1.18 and 1.60 fall/patient year. These were frequent in frail older adults on hemodialysis treatment. Falling relapses in the same group of patients caused serious consequences. Data on pre-end stage renal disease (ESRD) were scarce.; Conclusions: The risk of falling appears to be common in patients with renal dysfunction especially in older adults undergoing hemodialysis. On the other hand, we could not find any conclusive data on pre-ESRD patients.;</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mansur, Henrique Novais</author><author>Lovisi, Júlio César Moraes</author><author>Colugnati, Fernando Antonio Basile</author><author>Raposo, Nadia Rezende Barbosa</author><author>da Silva Fernandes, Natália Maria</author><author>Bastos, Marcus Gomes</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Association of frailty with endothelial dysfunction and its possible impact on negative outcomes in Brazilian predialysis patients with chronic kidney disease</title><secondary-title>BMC nephrology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>BMC nephrology</full-title></periodical><pages>157</pages><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2015</year></dates><isbn>1471-2369</isbn><notes>read
.
as risk for frailty
,

endothelial dysfunction

causal relationship in doubt</notes><research-notes>read
.
as risk for frailty
,

endothelial dysfunction

causal relationship in doubt</research-notes><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Mansur et al. - 2015 - Association of frailty with endothelial dysfunction and its possible impact on negative outcomes in Brazilian pre.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Noto-Kadou-Kaza, Befa</author><author>Teuwafeu, Denis Georges</author><author>Sabi, Kossi Akomola</author><author>Zenasni, Nadia</author><author>Amekoudi, Eyram Yoan Makafui</author><author>Tsevi, Claude Mawufemo</author><author>Mahamat, Maimouna</author><author>Bikinga, Yasminatou Aminata Wendkuuni</author><author>El Khayat, Selma</author><author>Zamd, Mohamed</author><author>Medkouri, Ghislaine</author><author>Benghanem, Mohamed Gharbi</author><author>Ramdani, Benyounes</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>[Falls among hemodialysis patients: Incidence and risk factors].</title><secondary-title>Nephrologie &amp; therapeutique</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Nephrologie &amp; therapeutique</full-title></periodical><pages>246-249</pages><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><keywords><keyword>80 and over</keyword><keyword>Accidental Falls</keyword><keyword>Adult</keyword><keyword>Aged</keyword><keyword>Female</keyword><keyword>Frail Elderly</keyword><keyword>Humans</keyword><keyword>Hypotension</keyword><keyword>Incidence</keyword><keyword>Male</keyword><keyword>Middle Aged</keyword><keyword>Prospective Studies</keyword><keyword>Renal Dialysis</keyword><keyword>Risk Factors</keyword><keyword>Sensation Disorders</keyword><keyword>Young Adult</keyword><keyword>complications</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2015</year></dates><accession-num>26093492</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.nephro.2015.03.004</electronic-resource-num><notes>read
.
only dialysis hypotension remained significant with a relative risk of 2.0 (1.8-2.2, p = 0.006).
.
occurrence of falls, p=0.047</notes><research-notes>read
.
only dialysis hypotension remained significant with a relative risk of 2.0 (1.8-2.2, p = 0.006).
.
occurrence of falls, p=0.047</research-notes><language>fre</language><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://noto-kadou-kaza2015.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Falls and mineral and bones disorders are both implicated in the occurrence of pathological fractures in patients undergoing chronic dialysis. However, data on falls among this population are rare. We carried out a prospective study during four weeks and included 70 patients on chronic hemodialysis with the main objectives being to evaluate the incidence of falls and factors related to it. At the end of the four weeks, 16 patients (22.86%) fell at least once, with a total of 17 falls during 4 weeks, giving an incidence of 3.2 falls per patient/year. The mean age was 40 +/- 16 years. Five patients (31.2%) had a past history of pathological fractures. Ten patients (62.5%) presented intra- and post-dialysis hypotension, six (37.5%) was diagnosed of gait disorders and two (12.5%) had sensory deficit of the lower limbs. Six patients (37.5%) presented frailty. Hypotension (P=0.004), frailty (P=0.047) and sensory deficit (P=0.049) were significantly associated with the occurrence of falls. The incidence of falls is relatively high in our hemodialysis patients and real risk factors exist. Hence, it is important to implement programs for falls prevention to reduce their incidence and impact.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>P., Sclauzero</author><author>G., Galli</author><author>G., Barbati</author><author>M., Carraro</author><author>G.O., Panzetta</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Role of components of frailty on quality of life in dialysis patients: A cross-sectional study</title><secondary-title>Journal of Renal Care</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Renal Care</full-title></periodical><pages>96-102</pages><volume>39</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Italy</keyword><keyword>aged</keyword><keyword>article</keyword><keyword>comorbidity</keyword><keyword>cross-sectional study</keyword><keyword>daily life activity</keyword><keyword>female</keyword><keyword>frail elderly</keyword><keyword>human</keyword><keyword>male</keyword><keyword>psychological aspect</keyword><keyword>quality of life</keyword><keyword>questionnaire</keyword><keyword>renal replacement therapy</keyword><keyword>very elderly</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2013</year></dates><pub-location>P. Sclauzero, S.C. Nefrologia e Dialisi, AOU Ospedali Riuniti, Strada di Fiume, 447, 34149 Trieste, Italy</pub-location><electronic-resource-num>10.1111/j.1755-6686.2013.12013.x</electronic-resource-num><language>English</language><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://sclauzero2013 (1).pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://www.embase.com/search/results?subaction=viewrecord&amp;from=export&amp;id=L52590875</url><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-6686.2013.12013.x</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Background: Many people on dialysis suffer a variety of conditions that can affect frailty (the condition or quality of being frail), such as comorbidities, disabilities, dependence, malnutrition, cognitive impairment and poor social conditions. Frailty is suspected to affect quality of life (QoL). Objectives: The study aimed to evaluate the effect of the different components of frailty on the QoL of people on dialysis. Methods: We enrolled 203 out of 233 prevalent patients on dialysis in the Trieste area of Italy. We applied the Short-Form 36 (SF-36) questionnaire, Activities of Daily Living, Instrumental Activities of Daily Living, Subjective Global Assessment scales and Karnofsky Index. In addition we analysed their social conditions. Results: Dependence, malnutrition and disability had a negative role on QoL. Living with family and good social-economic conditions were significantly related to a better QoL. Conclusions: Dependence, malnutrition, disability, poor social and economic conditions have a significant effect on life quality. The role of comorbidities appears to be less important. Screening of patients, nutritional and functional rehabilitation and prevention of social isolation appear to be indispensable in guaranteeing a satisfactory life quality. © 2013 European Dialysis and Transplant Nurses Association/European Renal Care Association.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Panzetta, G</author><author>Grignetti, M</author><author>Sceusa, R</author><author>Toigo, G</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>[Frail elderly in hemodialysis].</title><secondary-title>Giornale italiano di nefrologia : organo ufficiale della Societa italiana di nefrologia</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Giornale italiano di nefrologia : organo ufficiale della Societa italiana di nefrologia</full-title></periodical><pages>554-560</pages><volume>21</volume><issue>6</issue><keywords><keyword>Activities of Daily Living</keyword><keyword>Aged</keyword><keyword>Aged, 80 and over</keyword><keyword>Frail Elderly</keyword><keyword>Humans</keyword><keyword>Renal Dialysis</keyword><keyword>Risk Factors</keyword><keyword>Socioeconomic Factors</keyword><keyword>Survival Rate</keyword><keyword>mortality</keyword><keyword>standards</keyword><keyword>statistics &amp; numerical data</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2004</year></dates><accession-num>15593023</accession-num><notes>did not measure effects of frailty in CKD patients
.

repeated hospitalizations

early study</notes><research-notes>did not measure effects of frailty in CKD patients
.

repeated hospitalizations

early study</research-notes><language>ita</language><urls/><abstract>A new category of patients aged &gt;75 yrs, namely the elderly, is now being freely  admitted to hemodialysis (HD) and this category is becoming predominant. The absence of systematic studies makes this patient category almost indistinguishable from other categories, even though its peculiarity is now evident. At least 30-40% of individuals in this age bracket are expected to be dependent and/or frail, but the incidence of frailty is likely to be higher in the elderly undergoing HD. Due to severe physical and/or mental impairment and often because of strong social hardships, these patients rarely experience clinical stability and are dependent on third parties for their survival. Their care produces complex problems for welfare services and this has proved responsible for modifying the organization of renal care units. These repeated patient admissions to hospital are filling nephrology facilities, and the dialysis management -- mainly concerning outpatients -- requires a much greater use of facilities and staff than normal if compared to average dialysis patients. In 112 elderly patients consecutively admitted to the dialysis program over a period of 10 yrs, we identified 35 dependent or frail patients (31.2%), even taking into consideration only extreme degrees of infirmity. Dependence proved to be the only clinical parameter associated with survival (mortality at 6 months 23.6 vs. 10.6%, p&lt;0.01; Kaplan-Meier survival curves, p&lt;0.03 log-rank test), while comorbidities -- in particular cardiovascular -- that usually affect dialysis mortality rates, did not seem to be discriminating risk factors in the elderly. More precisely, with the confirmation of these data through wider case studies, the idea will be reinforced that, also in dialysis, the elderly must be constantly monitored for dependence and frailty, as is the case in any exclusively geriatric field. Prevention, as well as a therapeutic approach specifically modeled on these conditions, could help to improve the prognosis of this patient category, which is particularly difficult to deal with and is becoming predominant in dialysis units.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Poveda, V</author><author>Filgueiras, M</author><author>Miranda, V</author><author>Santos-Silva, A</author><author>Paul, C</author><author>Costa, E</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Frailty in End-Stage Renal Disease Patients under Dialysis and Its Association with Clinical and Biochemical Markers.</title><secondary-title>The Journal of frailty &amp; aging</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>The Journal of frailty &amp; aging</full-title></periodical><pages>103-106</pages><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Aged</keyword><keyword>Biomarkers</keyword><keyword>Cross-Sectional Studies</keyword><keyword>Female</keyword><keyword>Frail Elderly</keyword><keyword>Frailty</keyword><keyword>Health Status</keyword><keyword>Humans</keyword><keyword>Kidney Failure, Chronic</keyword><keyword>Male</keyword><keyword>Middle Aged</keyword><keyword>Portugal</keyword><keyword>Prevalence</keyword><keyword>Quality of Life</keyword><keyword>Renal Dialysis</keyword><keyword>blood</keyword><keyword>epidemiology</keyword><keyword>statistics &amp; numerical data</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2017</year></dates><accession-num>28555712</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.14283/jfa.2017.14</electronic-resource-num><notes>Whole text not attainable
.

An association between FRAIL score and increased depressive symptoms, presence of hypertension and decrease nutritional status was also found.</notes><research-notes>Whole text not attainable
.

An association between FRAIL score and increased depressive symptoms, presence of hypertension and decrease nutritional status was also found.</research-notes><language>eng</language><urls/><abstract>Frailty is a common complication in elderly patients with end-stage renal disease (ESRD) under dialysis, which is a strong risk factor for low quality of life, morbidity, and mortality. In this work, we aimed to evaluate the prevalence of frailty in a group of Portuguese ESRD patients, and its association with socio-demographic, clinical and biochemical markers. We performed a cross-sectional study with 83 ESRD patients (44 males and 39 females, 64.3 [+/-14.6] years old) on regular dialysis. The classification of the ESRD patients as robust, pre-frail and frail was performed using the FRAIL questionnaire. Social support, data about sociodemographic and comorbidities, and haematological, iron status, dialysis adequacy, nutritional and inflammatory markers were also evaluated. Our results confirmed that frailty is a highly prevalent condition in ESRD patients, particularly in female patients. An association between FRAIL score and increased depressive symptoms, presence of hypertension and decrease nutritional status was also found.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Shlipak, Michael G.</author><author>Fried, Linda F.</author><author>Crump, Casey</author><author>Bleyer, Anthony J.</author><author>Manolio, Teri A.</author><author>Tracy, Russell P.</author><author>Furberg, Curt D.</author><author>Psaty, Bruce M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Elevations of Inflammatory and Procoagulant Biomarkers in Elderly Persons With Renal Insufficiency</title><secondary-title>Circulation</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Circulation</full-title></periodical><pages>87-92</pages><volume>107</volume><issue>1</issue><keywords><keyword>coagulation</keyword><keyword>coronary disease</keyword><keyword>inflammation</keyword><keyword>kidney</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2003</year></dates><publisher>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1161/01.CIR.0000042700.48769.59</electronic-resource-num><notes>pro-inflammatory cytokines cause frailty in CKD patients</notes><research-notes>pro-inflammatory cytokines cause frailty in CKD patients</research-notes><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://01.CIR.0000042700.48769.59.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/01.CIR.0000042700.48769.59</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Background— Renal insufficiency has been associated with cardiovascular disease events and mortality in several prospective studies, but the mechanisms for the elevated risk are not clear. Little is known about the association of renal insufficiency with inflammatory and procoagulant markers, which are potential mediators for the cardiovascular risk of kidney disease. Methods and Results— The cross-sectional association of renal insufficiency with 8 inflammatory and procoagulant factors was evaluated using baseline data from the Cardiovascular Health Study, a population-based cohort study of 5888 subjects aged ≥65 years. C-reactive protein, fibrinogen, factor VIIc, and factor VIIIc levels were measured in nearly all participants; interleukin-6, intercellular adhesion molecule-1, plasmin-antiplasmin complex, and D-dimer levels were measured in nearly half of participants. Renal insufficiency was defined as a serum creatinine level ≥1.3 mg/dL in women and ≥1.5 mg/dL in men. Multivariate linear regression wa...</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Sy, John</author><author>Johansen, Kirsten L</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The impact of frailty on outcomes in dialysis.</title><secondary-title>Current opinion in nephrology and hypertension</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Current opinion in nephrology and hypertension</full-title></periodical><pages>537-542</pages><volume>26</volume><issue>6</issue><keywords><keyword>Aged</keyword><keyword>Chronic</keyword><keyword>Cognitive Dysfunction</keyword><keyword>Frail Elderly</keyword><keyword>Frailty</keyword><keyword>Geriatric Assessment</keyword><keyword>Humans</keyword><keyword>Prognosis</keyword><keyword>Quality of Life</keyword><keyword>Renal Dialysis</keyword><keyword>Renal Insufficiency</keyword><keyword>complications</keyword><keyword>diagnosis</keyword><keyword>mortality</keyword><keyword>therapy</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2017</year></dates><accession-num>28901990</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1097/MNH.0000000000000364</electronic-resource-num><notes>read
.
falls, fractures, cognitive impairment, vascular access failure, and poor quality of life.</notes><research-notes>read
.
falls, fractures, cognitive impairment, vascular access failure, and poor quality of life.</research-notes><language>eng</language><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://sy2017.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>PURPOSE OF REVIEW: Frailty is highly prevalent in the dialysis population and is associated with mortality. Recent studies have suggested that other dialysis outcomes are compromised in frail individuals. While we do not yet have a consensus as to the best measure of frailty, identification of these poor outcomes and their magnitude of association with frailty will help improve prognostication, allow for earlier interventions, and improve provider-to-patient communication. RECENT FINDINGS: The most widely used assessment of frailty is Fried's physical performance criteria. However, regardless of assessment method, frailty remains highly associated with mortality. More recently, frailty has been associated with falls, fractures, cognitive impairment, vascular access failure, and poor quality of life. Recent large cohort studies provide strong evidence that frailty assessment can provide important prognostic information for providers and patients both before and after initiation of dialysis. Trials aimed at improving frailty are limited and show the promise of augmenting quality of life, although more studies are needed to firmly establish mortality benefits. SUMMARY: We underscore the importance of frailty as a prognostic indicator and identify other recently established consequences of frailty. Widespread adoption of frailty assessment remains limited and researchers continue to find ways of simplifying the data collection process. Timely and regular assessment of frailty may allow for interventions that can mitigate the onset of poor outcomes and identify actionable targets for dialysis providers.</abstract></record></records></xml>
